<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consolatorie epistle to the afflicted catholikes, set foorth by Thomas Hide Priest</title>
            <author>Hide, Thomas, 1524-1597.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118132</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853341</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853341</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18721</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18721)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1207:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consolatorie epistle to the afflicted catholikes, set foorth by Thomas Hide Priest</title>
                  <author>Hide, Thomas, 1524-1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[118] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Maes, for Iohn Lion,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Louaine :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579 VVith priuilege.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K4 (-K4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATORIE EPISTLE TO THE AFFLICTED catholikes, ſet foorth by THOMAS HIDE Prieſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Be ſtrong, and take a Good hart vnto you, al you that put your trust in our lord.</p>
               <bibl>Pſalm. 30.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>ECCE AGNVS DEI.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at Louaine by Iohn Maes, for Iohn Lion. 1579.</p>
            <p>VVITH PRIVILEGE. <hi>Subſig. Strick.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>The ouen proueth the potters veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, ſo doth temptation of trouble trie the righteous.</p>
                  <bibl>Eccleſ. 27.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>Our lord knoweth how to deliuer the godlie out of temptation, and how to reſerue the vniust to be poniſhed, at the daie of iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                  <bibl>2. Pet. 2.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>You muſt ſuffer patientlie, that you maie be knowen to be his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for whom you ſuffer.</p>
                  <bibl>Zepherin. epist.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:2"/>
            <head>A CONSOLATORIE EPISTLE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is writen,<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that <hi>Chriſte and his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples vvent into a ſhippe, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſodai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelie aroſe a greate tempeſt in the ſea, ſo that the ſhippe vvas couered vvith vvaues. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte ſlept. His diſciples avvaked hym and ſaide, maiſter ſaue vs, vve periſhe. Chriſte ſaide vnto them, vvhy are you feareful, you of litle faithe? Then he aroſe, rebuked the vvindes, and there folovved a greate calme.</hi> We muſt ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of Chriſtes workes,<note place="margin">Grego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h mel <hi>2</hi> it cap. <hi>18.</hi> Luc.</note> that we beleaue them to be don in veritie, and to implie an other thinge in ſignification, to ſhewe one thinge by power, and to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie an other in myſterie. It lacketh not myſterie, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte and his diſciples went into a ſhippe, and that this ſhippe was te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſted. You haue heard
<pb facs="tcp:18721:3"/>
de Chriſtes facte, marke the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie.<note place="margin">Aug ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. <hi>14.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e verb Domini.</note> This ſhippe reſembled the churche militant, wherin al chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſengers do ſaile, and be toſſed with tempeſtes, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les they driue towarde theire co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>untrie, the quiet hauen of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that is the churche trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant. The ſea reſembleth the courſe of the worlde, which is alwayes troublous. And by the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſte is ſignified al ſuche preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and perſecution, as they muſt expecte, that folowe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte into this ſhippe. It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to ſainct Iohn the wel-beloued Apoſtle of Chriſte,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.</note> that the churche ſhould haue greate perſecution. <hi>Beholde the diuel ſhal caſt ſome of you into priſon to be tempted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda in <hi>2.</hi> ca. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c.</note> 
               <hi>and you ſhal haue tribulation ten dayes.</hi> By the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of ten dayes is ſignified, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ten perſecutions which the churche ſuffered vnder the Emperours, or els the whole tracte of troubles, which ſhe ſhal endure in hir peregrinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:18721:3"/>
There hath ben no age of men, nor courſe of time ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, wherin this ſhippe, (that is to ſaye the militant churche of Chriſte) hath not ben tempeſted.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36</note> 
               <hi>The vngodlye drevve out their ſvvorde, bente their bovve to caſt dovvne the ſimple, and to ſlaie ſuch as goo the right vvaie.</hi> Thes wordes of the prophet were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refied after Chriſtes aſcenſion,<note place="margin">Augu in Pſal. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</hi> Ruffin in Pſal. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> when there aroſe greate tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, to wit diuers perſecutions againſt the churche, open perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and ſecret perſecution, perſecution violent, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution fraudulent, perſecution of tyrannie, and perſecution of hereſie, the one openlie, the other ſecretlie, the one by ſwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, the other by worde. Of theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes, hereſie was more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarious to the churche,<note place="margin">Auguſt. tract <hi>5.</hi> in euang. Ioan.</note> then ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie. For hereſie tranſforme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the hir ſelfe into the Angel of light, proceadeth gilfullie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth the ſimple, ſtriketh gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſelie with the ſworde of the
<pb facs="tcp:18721:4"/>
tonge, and ſhedeth bloud cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, by killinge Chriſte in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie dealeth not with ſcripture, not with drifte of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, nor by order of iuſte prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, but by crueltie, and dint of ſworde. Yet hath the churche gayned more by tyrannie then by hereſie, for tyrannie maketh martyrs, hereſie begetteth Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtats.<note place="margin">Tertul. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Of them that perſecuted the churche with tyrannie and hereſie, they were moſt ingrate and greateſt perſecutors, who beinge ſome time chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and fallinge from chriſtianitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came profeſſed enemies to the chriſtian religion.<note place="margin">Theodor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> ſo was Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens the Emperour, who of a catholike became an Arian. ſo was Iulianus, who borne of chriſtian parentes, and brought vp by learned chriſtians, beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Apoſtata.<note place="margin">Euſeb li. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>8</hi>
               </note> ſo was Licinius who of a chriſtian, became a perſecutor.<note place="margin">Euagr. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> There lacked not in this parte, ſome nomber of the feminine tribe, to put to
<pb facs="tcp:18721:4"/>
their ſhrewde heades and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, as Theodora, Iuſtina,<note place="margin">Hiero. 4. cieſc.</note> Philomenes, Priſca, Maximil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, and Lucilla. It is not my fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intention to enlarge of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, nor of perſecutors, but brefelie to ſhewe to the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted catholikes of our tyme, that yf now they finde al poſſible op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions vnder hereſie and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie, it may not ſeme ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vnto them, yf they conſider how Chriſtes ſhippe was coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the waues, how the churche hath ben perſecuted eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from hir infancie, and that ſhe lacketh not at this time hir Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes, hir Iulians, hir Lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, hir Theodoras, hir Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, hir Lucinas. This pointe I wil touche, a pointe not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to note, why Chriſte permitteth his churche to be ſo ſore tempted, and why the diuel rayſed ſo manie blouddie bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes of cruel perſecutions, in the verie prime of the churche. It is the corruption of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:18721:5"/>
nature, to forget our dutiful ſeruice to God, when we be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and holde our deſires in quiet.<note place="margin">Grego. ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mel. <hi>17.</hi> in cap <hi>4.</hi> Matth.</note> We gaſe vpon the gaie glitterings of the wanton worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, wee feede our appetites with the delicate cheriſhinges of the fleſhe, ſo that our heartes begine to be eſtrainged from God, and to leeſe the ſenſe and feelinge of godlines, vntil God ſende vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that geueth vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge. When proſperitie had brought in libertie, and impunitie of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne corrupted diſcipline,<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> when chriſtians declined from deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conuerſation, and committed greate diſorders, God waxed angrie, and ſterred againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, againſt their churches, againſt ther prieſtes and paſtors, the puiſſante power of perſecutors, to reuenge his conceiued anger.<note place="margin">Cyprian de lap.</note> When longe peace had corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Godes heauenlie diſcipline, and feruour of faithe beganne to coole in the houſe of God, God began iudgement in his
<pb facs="tcp:18721:5"/>
owne houſe, and by ſeueritie of correction, erected faithe that laie a ſleape, and as it were in contempte. Semblablie God dealeth now with his people, knowinge the lewſenes of thei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re life, and ſeinge the drines of their faithe, he rayſeth vp a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate tempeſte, wherin they be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſlie toſſed, with manye hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the vnquiet ſea. Certes for many hundred yeares, the chriſtian worlde, the chriſtian religion, the faithe catholike, was not ſo mightelie ſhaken as it hath ben in thes later tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of our times, when bothe violent and fraudulent perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion haue aſſaide euen by penal lawes, to raſe out of chriſtian mens heartes, the general fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of Chriſte, and to perſecute them that further not ſuch a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cial faithe, as the ſpirite of the worlde teacheth.</p>
            <p>To you therfore (derelie belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued countrie men) to you that be afflicted catholikes for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:6"/>
in what caſe and place ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you be, I addreſſe this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatorie epiſtle, wherin my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour is to declare ſuche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes, as the ſelfe cauſe of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſemeth to yelde. Seinge now the violent windes blowe and bluſter not onelie againſte the kingedomes of the worlde, but againſte the churche that is the kingedome of god, and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge that they haue ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the ſhippe manye, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye loſt chriſtians, I offer vnto you that yet remaine and ſuffer in the ſhippe then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes, euen out of the bodie and boſome of religion. I make common to you that ſuffer for religion ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes, as I labored to gaine to my ſelfe in the greate tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of thes countries, wherin were vſed manye miſcheuous meanes to deface religion.</p>
            <p>Firſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recogniſe you with me, why and for what cauſe you ſuffer. Yf you ſuffer for any hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb facs="tcp:18721:6"/>
facte, or enormious ſynne, <hi>the name of God is blaſphemed emong you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.</note> Yf you ſuffer for murther, thefte, or ſacrilege, you ſuffer with diſhonor, ſhame, and ſynne. Yf you be felons, there is an haulter, yf you be traitors, there is an axe, yf you be hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, there is a ſtake, fagot, and fire. But the cauſe of your ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringe is knowen, and by your knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> actes teſtified to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of the chriſtian worlde. It is knowen, that you ſuffer as chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for Chriſtes ſake, that you ſuffer as catholikes for the catholike faithe, and that you ſuffer as open chriſtians, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſant catholikes. You ſtode in the firſte fronte againſt the violent innouation of religion. You were depriued of honors, of lordeſhippes, of landes, and liuelehood. You haue ſuſtained great and longe affliction, you ſuſtaine yet diſgrace, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, and banyſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And why? is it a faute to be a chriſtian?
<pb facs="tcp:18721:7"/>
Is it ſinne to confeſſe the faithe of Chriſte? or is it blame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be a member of Chriſtes catholike churche? If you be chriſtians, yf you be catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, yf you be afflicted chriſtian catholikes for the catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, If (I ſaye) when you ſtande in thes termes, there be no other cauſe why you ſuffer, then ſurelie you ſuffer directlie, for the catholike cauſe. In the houſe of God there is no cauſe more honorable, no cauſe more glorious, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the catholike cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. This cauſe almightie God commended, when he commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the worlde to heare his ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Chriſte. For this cauſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte came into the worlde, and he ſuffered more tribulation, then any creature is able to ſuffer. Had there ben any cauſe more noble then this, Chriſte wolde haue choſen it, and ſuffered for it.</p>
            <p>But there was no worne that made a more manifeſte ſhewe of true vertue, there was no
<pb facs="tcp:18721:7"/>
trial ſo farre from al ſuſpition, as to ſuffer for religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte hath his ſainctes in heauen that honour hym in quiet loue: ſo hath he his ſainctes in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, that honour hym with trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled loue. As there is in heauen nothinge more precious, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the glorious loue of his ſainctes: ſo is there in earthe no thing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re acceptable, then the afflicted loue of the iuſte, who for his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, ſuffer for his religion. Yf there be no creature,<note place="margin">Aug de ciuit. Dei lib <hi>10.</hi> cap <hi>1.</hi> Idem de ſpirit &amp; lit. c. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth God in rule of religion but man onelie, yf religion be a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice propre to God, and be ſo called becauſe the ſoule of man fallinge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God throughe ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, rebindeth hir ſelfe againe to him by that ſeruice, and man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhewe to God no other ſupreme ſeruice, nor ſoueraigne honor but religion, then ſurelie it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that man hath bounde him ſelfe vnto, and then is it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, (that is to ſaye a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of conſcience) to kepe that
<pb facs="tcp:18721:8"/>
do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and rather to ſuffer for it, then to incurre Godes diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Nor ſhoulde any wel infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doubte, whether he might ſuffer for this cauſe, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce taketh awaye doubte, and to doubte is lacke of faithe, for fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the doubteth not but that we ſhould ſuffer, and Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude chooſeth rather to ſuffer, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to leſe pietie. Yf good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſuffered torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge the ſecrettes of their frein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſhould not wee ſuffer for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruinge the ſacramentes of our faithe? Yf euil me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer for wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges don to the common weale, ſhal not good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer for ſuche rightes, as belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the churche of Chriſte? Manye haue died in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>battes whiles they adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tured to helpe their freindes, maye we die for mennes ſake, and refuſe to die for God? what ſhould I ſpeake of the Gentiles, who ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained greuous paines in doubt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful affaires, onelie for vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? Should we chriſtians refuſe
<pb facs="tcp:18721:8"/>
to ſuffer for veritie, what they ſought to ſuffer, for vanitie? I neede ſaye no more. Chriſt the teacher of ſufferaunce and humi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie, ſuffered al that he ſuffered, to make his churche glorious, and he ſuffered firſte to ſhewe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample to vs, to ſuffer after. And after him ſo manye glorious Martyrs, and membres of his churche ſuffered for the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſe of the churche, that now to ſuffer for the ſame, it ſhould not ſeeme impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the dutie of a chriſtian. Yf now then (you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted catholikes) you ſuffer for this cauſe, (as in dede you ſuffer) doubteles in this name you glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie god, in this name you honor God. And what tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes deſerue you now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you feare god, liue in his lawes, obey his churche, and chooſe rather to endure gree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> to beare wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſake to God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to folowe the goſpel of the worlde? It were no praiſe for you, yf you ſuffered for your ſinnes, but when you ſuffer for that cauſe, wich is iuſtifiable
<pb facs="tcp:18721:9"/>
to al the chriſtian worlde, which is commended of al good men, and approued of God him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, as Godes owne proper and perſonal cauſe, when now (I ſaye) you ſuffer for that cauſe, doubtles this is tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke worthie of God. This cauſe is ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portante, that none can ſuffer for it, but by the gratious gifte of God, and God geaueth this gifte to none, but to his ſpecial freindes. This ioyneth you nea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vnto God, cauſeth you to ſet leſſe by the worlde, diminiſheth your paines in purgatorie, and encreaſeth your final rewarde in heauen. This is ſuch a cauſe, as for the which who ſo hath not the gifte to ſuffer, ought to ſeeke it by praier, and penance. So longe as you ſuffer for this cauſe, you haue litle cauſe to feare the power of your migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aduerſaries.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>VVhat is to them cauſe of perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, God vvil turne to your ſaluation. for vnto you it is geuen not onelie to beleue in
<pb facs="tcp:18721:9"/>
Chriſte, but to ſuffer alſo for his ſake.</hi> Marke the gifte, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the grace. God that is the geauer of giftes and graces, God that hath called you to his eternal glorie by Chriſte Ieſu, wil make you perfecte,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> wil ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthen you, and eſtabliſhe you, after you haue ſuffered a litle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. In dede it is but litle, <hi>Yet doth it prepare vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>an excedinge and eternal vveight of glorie.</hi> For what ſeke you in this ſufferinge? Not to folowe the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of men, which be corrupte and crooked, but to do the wil of God, that is iuſt and righte. And for what ſuffer you? not for felonie or thefte, not for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or treaſon, not for hereſie or ſacrilege, but for truthe and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, for vnitie and veritie, for faithe and religion. You ſuffer not for vice, but for vertue, you ſuffer not for the thinges that be temporal, but for the thinges which be eternal. Reioyſe you conſtant chriſtians, reioyſe you
<pb facs="tcp:18721:10"/>
afflicted catholikes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>You that be novve pertakers of Chriſtes paſsion, ſhal reioyſe muche more at the reuelation of his glorie.</hi> What Chriſte ſuffered in the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſage of his deathe, he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered as head,<note place="margin">Augu in Pſal. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> it remained that he was to ſuffer in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 1.</note> You be his members. <hi>You fulfil that in your fleſhe, that lacked of his paſsion, and you fulfil it for his bodie, vvhich is the churche.</hi> Chriſte ſuffereth no more in fleſhe wherin he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heauen, but he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in your fleſhe, which yet trauaileth on the earthe. What lacked in the head,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in pſ. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> is ſupplied in the members. And therfore you ſuffer as members of his bodie for his bodie, which is the churche, and you ſuffer for the trial of your faithe, which is tried to this ende, that it might be founde to honor whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte commeth, in whom you bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, for whom you ſuffer, and by whom you ſhal receaue the
<pb facs="tcp:18721:10"/>
ende of your faithe, <hi>euen the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of your ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seinge then religion is the ſoueraigne honor,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> and the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſupreme ſeruice that you owe to God, ſeinge it is the moſt glorious and honorable cauſe, for which you can ſuffer, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of no creature, loue of no fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, feare of no aduerſitie, ſhould withdrawe you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this cauſe. Loue of parentes and countrie, loue of wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, loue of goodes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, loue of liuelehood and life, muſt geue place to this. They that for this cauſe forſake the temporal welth of the world ſhal receaue the ſpiritual bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges of God our lorde. This ſaith our lorde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 19</note> 
               <hi>Euerie man that forſaketh hys houſe, or hys bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or ſiſters, or father, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or vvife, or children, or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des for my name ſake, ſhal receaue an hundred folde.</hi> He promiſeth more then this, to them that dye
<pb facs="tcp:18721:11"/>
for his ſake.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 16</note> This ſaith our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. <hi>He that leeſeth his life for me, ſhal finde the ſame.</hi> Ther be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities of chriſtian dewties, diuerſities of honor, obedience, and loue. There is a loue dewe vnto our parentes, and this hath his limitation. Who ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them aboue Chriſte, is not Chriſtes diſciple, nay whoſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them not for Chriſte, is not his diſciple, and he that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not al, and beareth not Chriſtes croſſe for Chriſtes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, can not be his diſciple. When faithe is called in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.</note> when chriſtians be conuented for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Godes cauſe muſt be anſwered, they be our mothers, they be our brothers, which do the wil of our father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 12</note> If they beleue in Chriſte, they muſt preferre vs that figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te for Chriſte, yf they beleue not, let the deade burie the deade.<note place="margin">Hiero. epist. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> There is a loue dewe vnto our natural father, ſo longe as he withdraweth vs not from our
<pb facs="tcp:18721:11"/>
heauenlie father. <hi rend="margQuotes">We muſt not acknowledge any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent age, kinred, ſtocke, or other creature, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they acknowledge God theire creator.<note place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epist. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> Our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes may doo what ſhal beſt like them of theire goodes and ſubſtance, with our ſoules they haue not to doo. Our ſoules be not theirs by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, but his, to whom we be regenerate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epist. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Thoughe thy nephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we a litle ladde and playnge boye hange aboute thy necke, thoughe thy mourninge mother with re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te heares and blubbered chekes ſhewe thee hir pappes wherwith ſhe gaue thee ſucke, thoughe thy feble father lye at thy threſholde, paſſe by thy father, paſſe by thy mother with drie eyes, and haſten to the croſſe of <hi rend="margQuotes">Chriſte, crueltie in this caſe, is the onelie kinde of pietie,</hi> and pietie for God, is no crueltie.<note place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epist. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> Ther is an honor and obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce dew to princes and ciuil ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the worlde. Thes dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:18721:12"/>
alſo haue their limitation. The children of Iſrael ſaide vnto their ruler Ioſue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſue</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>As vve haue obeyed Moyſes, ſo vvil vvee obeye thee, looke onelie to this, that our lorde God be vvith thee, as he vvas vvith Moyſes.</hi> As who wold ſaye, we wil obeye thee ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, as thou obeieſt God, God is to be obeied, and ſo is Ioſue, God before Ioſue, God aboue Ioſue, and rather God then Ioſue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Daniel.</hi> 3</note> The children of Iſrael obeied kinge Nabuchodonoſor inal that he might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde by authoritie of a kinge. But when he proclamed, that his ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhoulde kneele downe and adore his Idol, they denied that obedience.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Daniel.</hi> 6</note> Daniel obeied kinge darius in externe matters, but when the kinge gaue out edicte, that whoſo prayed to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God but to him ſhould be caſte to the lions, he forſoke the courte, entred his chamber, and there praied thriſe adaye vpon his knees. Likewiſe Matha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias
<pb facs="tcp:18721:12"/>
ſaide.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Macha. cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>VVe vvil obeie the lavve of our fathers, vve vvil not harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the kinge.</hi> Was it not obiected to Chriſtes Apoſtles, that they contraried the ſenate and counſelers? and therevnto S. Peter made this breefe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>VVe muſt obeye God ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. li. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> What time the holie man and bleſſed Martyr ſainct Policarpe was broughte before the proconſul, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſweare to Ceſar, and to reuile Chriſte, he made this anſwer. I haue ſerued Chriſte foure ſcore yeares and ſyxe, and to this daye Chriſte neuer iniured mee, nor dyd ought, why I ſhould reuile him. My ſelfe am a Chriſtian, <hi rend="margQuotes">and wee chriſtians be taughte to geue to princes, and ſeculer powers ſuche honor, as is not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to our religion.</hi> In thes dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties then, this is the limitation, our ſoueraigne loue, honor, and obedience, is dewe onely to god,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:13"/>
and thes may be done with oute diſhonor or preiudice to princes, as the children of Iſrael did, as Daniel did, as Mathathias did, as the Apoſtles did, as ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte Polycarpe did, who obeied God, and men, but rather God then men, who gaue to Ceſar what belonged to Ceſar, and to God what belonged to God. Kinges, princes, and pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates of the worlde, be the ſeruantes of God, God is their maiſter, we may not obeie the ſeruant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the maiſter.<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>11.</hi> quaest. qui re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</note> When infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour authoritie commaundeth what we ſhould not doo, we muſt refuſe that authoritie, and feare the ſuperior power. Yf the Emperour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde one thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and God an other, he muſt <hi rend="margQuotes">pardon vs, thoughe wee obeie not, he threateneth priſon, God threateneth hel.</hi> In Gods cauſe, we muſt obeie God and not me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when men be contrarie to God, nor ſhoulde we therfore be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led diſobedient ſubiectes, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented
<pb facs="tcp:18721:13"/>
perſones, yf in Godes matters wee preferre God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men. This is the ſcope I leauel at, that our ſoueraigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, muſt be to God in al dewties without exception, and that in the houſe of God, there is no greater cauſe nor greater obedience, then to ſuffer for the loue of God. Sainct Paule en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with this loue, and with the zeale of Godes houſe, braſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e oute thes wordes. <hi>VVho ſhal ſeparat vs from the loue of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſhal tribulation or anguiſhe, or perſecution, or honger, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, or peril, or ſvvorde? I am ſure that neyther deathe, nor lyfe, neyther angelles, nor rule, nor povver, neyther thinges pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor thinges to come, nor hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe, nor lovve, nor any other creature ſhal be able to ſeparate vs, from the loue of God.</hi> What ſterred vp the ſtoute ſtandinge of the Confeſſors, the blouddye battaile of the Martyres, the chaſte combat of the virgins,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:14"/>
but the loue of Godes houſe? This moued ſ. Athanaſius that holie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſor to ſaye,<note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. li. <hi>10</hi> cap. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> let vs go to meete with our perſecutor, that <hi rend="margQuotes">he may perceaue how much greater the power of him is that defendeth vs, then the power of him that perſecuteh vs.</hi> This moued that couragious capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and glorious Martyr.<note place="margin">Baſil in Cord. Mart.</note> S. Gordius whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was exhorted to kepe his faithe ſecrete in his hearte, and to denie it with his <hi rend="margQuotes">mouthe, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie to ſaye, <hi>corde cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus,</hi> we beleue in hearte to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe with mouthe to ſaluation, God is my helper, I feare not what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doo. That noble woman, and holie martyr</hi> S. Iulitta,<note place="margin">Baſil ſer. in Iulit.</note> complained to the iudge of iniuries do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vnto hir, ſoughte for iuſtice at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. His anſwer was, that nor ſhee nor any ſuche aſ ſhee was (which adored not the emperors gods, which were not of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours <hi rend="margQuotes">religion,) ſhoulde expecte iuſtice, or pleade wronge. Why
<pb facs="tcp:18721:14"/>
then (ſayde ſhe) I haue done, farewel my liuinge, adewe my</hi> life. Conſider you nowe, you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted catholikes that God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth you worthye to ſuffer for his loue, and to render your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his holye na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, wherin you haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte your ſelues, that God reputeth you for his freindes, for to his freindes he geueth this ſpecial gifte. You ſuffer wronges, you ſuſtaine the princes indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you beare the diſpleaſure of the magiſtrates for your obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to gods churche. This poynte you chooſe not, and gladlye would you haue it otherwyſe. But yf you chooſe it for pieties ſake, your choice, is iuſtifiable. S. Baſil in the like caſe made this <hi rend="margQuotes">anſwer.<note place="margin">Theodo. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> Of the emperours fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe fauour and furthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I do wel eſteeme ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as it is ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with godlines, without that I holde it pernitious. It was ſaide to Maris a deuoute cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke,</hi> be of the Emperours religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:15"/>
and he wyl make thee an Arche biſhope. I may not ſo be ſaide he, leaſt I offende God that is <hi rend="margQuotes">my Emperour. His promotion I wil not take, becauſe he is not of my religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18</note>This is our lordes leſſon, <hi>Let hym be vnto thee as an heathen and publican, that heareth not the churche.</hi> As the heathen which neuer came to the faithe peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth: ſo doth the heritike that hath forſaken the faithe. Out of the churche no religion can ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, no faithe can ſaue. he that is founde out of the churche, is a ſtranger fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God. Nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he haue God for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Aug. li <hi>4</hi> de ſym. cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> that hath not the churche for his mother. O you trobeled chriſtians, and you afflicted ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, beholde, here haue you manye greate and ghoſtlie comfortes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider. For what ſeeke you, when you ſuffer for the churche? Nothinge (I wene) but what the ſelfe cauſe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:15"/>
to wyt, that you do the wyl of our lorde, which you be ſure to finde in his churche. For of his churche our lorde ſayde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſaiae</hi> 62</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt be called a citie ſought for, and not forſaken.</hi> In his churche you can not be decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his wyl, for in his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he is alwaye reſiant, and therfore is his churche called,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 48</note> 
               <hi>Dominus ibidem, Our lorde is therein.</hi> Note here what tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes and trobles the churche hath had. The churche hath ben laide at, and ſhaken from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie parte, and quarter of the worlde. The Archeheretikes of eache parte, men of condemned memorie, gaue the firſt onſet with violent ſhotte of tonges, and al poſſible policie of penne. The crooked crewe of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious of ſpringe put to theire batteries, and ſhaked the weake walles of them, that were not faſte in faithe. The ſhippe nowe tottered, the ſhippe nowe was toſſed with many contrarious
<pb facs="tcp:18721:16"/>
windes. Many were ſhaken in the ſhippe, and al made wrecke, that kepte not within bourde. The ſterrers of this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt were fraudulente perſecutors, who could temper theire tale in ſuche wyſe, couer theire hypocriſie with ſo liuelie colours, that they obtayned credite of good natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.<note place="margin">Tertul. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. cap <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> To ſuche men it is agreinge to racke the ſcriptures, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte the fathers, and with ſweete wordes to tole and baet the readers that ſee not the hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of falſehood, wherwith they choke them.<note place="margin">Ambr de fide cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. contra Arian. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Becauſe thes miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaninge men, haue in outwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſhewe manye poyntes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the catholikes, they intrappe incircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpecte readers, and infecte the ſimple beleauers, as it were with one droppe of poyſon, amonge manye ſofte <hi rend="margQuotes">and ſugered wordes. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie hath ben alwaye acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with tyrannie, that vſeth world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye wyſedome and peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> to further hir proceadinges.
<pb facs="tcp:18721:16"/>
Yet coulde neyther of thes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede ſo farre hitherto, as to put out the catholike name.<note place="margin">Theodo. li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> They vſed many ſuttle ſleightes with the catholikes, as Iulianus vſed, when he byd his ſouldiers (that woulde receaue their paie) caſt frankenſence into the fire,<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. <hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> as Theodotus vſed, when he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a byſhoprike to Natalius,<note place="margin">Theod li. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>17</hi>
               </note> as Modeſtus vſed, when he went aboute to perſwade Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil to yelde to the time, and to vſe the fauoure of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. But faire meanes, fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and flatterie could not preuaile againſt the faſt, firme, and wel vnderſtandinge catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. foule meanes, crueltie and violence lacked not,<note place="margin">Euſeb li. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte, diſgrace, indignities, abaſement were added. Aulters were raſed, churches deſtroyed,<note place="margin">Euag. li. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> Sezom. li. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> prieſtes depriued, catholikes iniured by impriſonmentes and tormentes. Then were not catholikes permitted to beare <hi rend="margQuotes">office in the common weale,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:17"/>
onely becauſe they were catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.<note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus lib. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Now were al factions and faſhions of pretended religions ſuffered to make their aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles, and openlie to vſe their religion, but onelie the catholike. Now were biſhopes and prieſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled</hi> oute of their churches, ſpoyled of theire goodes, and called before lay iudges. Now were the priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s repleniſhed with chriſtians that were not ſuffered to be releaued, ſuche was the merceleſſe tyrannie of the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors. Certs thes were greate te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes, thes were bothe frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent, and violent perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yet dyd not thes preuaile. And why? <hi>Dominus ibidem.</hi> Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe now the world like the bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge ſea boyie and breake out his force, thoughe the potenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the worlde execute theire furye againſt you, feare you not, faile you not, fainte you not, you I ſaye that ſayle in the ſhippe which nowe is tempeſted with contrarious windes, feare you
<pb facs="tcp:18721:17"/>
not, our lorde is with you, you be ſafe, <hi>Dominus ibidem.</hi> Aſee, who is that lorde by whom you be gouerned in this ſhippe.<note place="margin">Ambr. lib. de Sal. ca. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> Chriſt the ſonne of God is hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted into the maſt of the ſhippe, that is on the croſſe. God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gouerneth the hinder par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, the holie ghoſte ſitteth in the foreparte. There be xij. roers in this ſhippe, to wyt the twelue Apoſtles, and thes driue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the ſhippe, bringinge hir through the ſtraightes of this trobleſom ſea into the quiet por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.<note place="margin">Aug ſer. <hi>14.</hi> de verb. de.</note> Chriſte our lorde that prayed for his churche, doth ſtil praie. Thoughe this ſhippe be toſſed, <hi rend="margQuotes">yet can ſhe not be drowned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſte praieth.<note place="margin">Chryſoſ. ho. <hi>24</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> Math. oper. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perf.</note>
               </hi> Thoughe this ſhippe be ſhaken with the violent windes of ſeculer atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, yet is ſhe ſafe from wracke, becauſe Chriſte gouerneth. And the holie ghoſte our lorde, that ſitteth in the fore parte of the ſhippe, ſtrengtheneth al ſuch as bee windeſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the holie ghoſte
<pb facs="tcp:18721:18"/>
dilateth the heartes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that be in tribulation. When Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte tolde his diſciples that they ſhould be accuſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10</note> conuented, and reuiled, for his names ſake, he tolde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo that he would not leaue them comfortleſſe. <hi>I vvil ſende you a comfortor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.</note> This comfortor gaue them ſtrengthe to beare al that the malice of the worlde, was able to laie vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It came to paſſe as Chriſte foretolde, they were caſte oute, conuented, and reuiled. did they grudge at it, did they murmure for it?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</note> The ſtorie ſaithe, <hi>They vvent oute from the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel houſe reioyſinge, that they vvere vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to ſuffer reuiles for the name of Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Paulus and Silas vvere put in priſon, and vvhipped cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> they did not repine, the ſtorie ſaithe? <hi>They ſange at midnighte, praienge and praiſinge our lorde.</hi> This ioye in this correction, this iocunditie of ſpirite in this tribulation, came of the holie ghoſte, that ſitteth at the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte
<pb facs="tcp:18721:18"/>
of the ſhippe, and geueth comfort in al tempeſtes and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations. This promiſe of comforte extended not onelie to Chriſtes diſciples, but in them to theire ofſpringe, and to the whole corps of Chriſtes chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wherſoeuer it be ſcatered in diſperſion. Who emboldened the perſecuted Chriſtians, to ſtande in the confeſſion of their faithe ſo conſtantlie, to profeſſe theire religion ſo confidentlie, euen to the face of the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, when they made thes ſtou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te <hi rend="margQuotes">aſſeuerations? <hi>Ego Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſum.</hi> I am a chriſtian.<note place="margin">Hila lib. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Catholicus ſum,</hi> I am a catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. <hi>Arianus non ſum,</hi> I am not an Arian. <hi>Haereticus eſſe nolo,</hi> I wil not be an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike.</hi> They were nickenamed,<note place="margin">Tripart. lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>7</hi> Hiſt. eccl. lib. <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> called men of Galile, called Homouſions and murtherers of Prophetes. The tyran ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed againſt them. <hi>Ad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtias,</hi> awaye with thes wretched chriſtians, awaye with them,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:19"/>
ſende them to the beaſtes, haue them to the lyons, hale them to the leopardes, awaye with thes naughtie wretches to the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, let them digge metalles.</p>
            <p>Now were thes miſerable men ſent <hi>ad campum Martyru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> where they were done to deathe. Now did the cutthrotes ſcoure theire ſwordes, in the bowels of the chriſtians. Now did the bloud-ſuckers dyp and waſhe their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, in the bloudde of the ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Who now did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte them, who now did ſtrengthen them, but the holie ghoſte, that gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the foreparte of the ſhippe, and comforteth the windeſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al tempeſtes and tribulation. To caſte a litle more to this, this comforte hath wel appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in thes latter perſecutions of our times. What halteringe, what hanginge, what hewinge downe of chriſtians, what mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deringe, what quateringe, what martyringe of catholikes hath there ben, ſince the partie prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb facs="tcp:18721:19"/>
began his newe no goſpel? What miſcheuous machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue the ſectaries practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to vnderproppe theire rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous religion? What lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tragedies haue they made, that nowe ſhake ſo mightelie the whole frame of Chriſtes fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the? And yet notwithſtandinge al theire poſſible oppreſſions, al theire pernitious plottes, faithe endureth, the churche ſtandeth, the catholike encreaſeth. And of this you that be in this ſtorme tottered and toſſed, do ſee what you comforte your ſelues in. As there be manye in manye quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our countrie, that ſuffer for the catholike cauſe: ſo be there manie that be broughte by theire ſufferinge, to knowe the catholike name, to enquire of the catholike churche, and to learne to confeſſe the catholike faithe. Yea there be many that neuer knewe the catholike reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which now in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon trobles of catholikes come
<pb facs="tcp:18721:20"/>
vnto it, receaue it, beleue it, and ſuffer for it. It may be preſumed by common intendement, that there is not lefte amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you any nomber of the catholike race. In dede it is rather miraculous then maruelous there ſhould be any, conſideringe ther hath not ben for ſome number of yeares any outwarde face, any open exerciſe of the catholike faithe, conſideringe there is no place, where catholikes be not pried for, apprehended and impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, no priſon ſo vile where they bee not harbored, yea thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which were ordayned for theifes, murtherers, bankerou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, heretikes, and treitors, be made the lodginges of holie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of reuerend biſhopes, of prieſtes, of gentlemen, and gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, finallie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideringe the lawes of the realme be againſte the catholikes, and that catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be depriued, ſpoyled, hated, diſgraced, perſecuted, and ſome of them executed. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:18721:20"/>
al this, Godes churche hath hir faitheful flocke, that confeſſeth the catholike truthe openlie, maugre the diuel, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and tyrannie. And hot with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge al worldelie diſgraces, ouertwhartes, iniuries, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and execution, yet is there lefte ſome good number, that neuer bowed theire knees to Baal, neuer receaued the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded communion, neyther went to the ſchiſmatical ſeruice. Yea ſome nomber that be readye to render their goodes to the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and their ſoules to God, as willinge in this quarrel to dye, as to liue. Bleſſed be the name of God that hath rayſed a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike youthe, to ſupplye the ruful ruine of them, which haue periſhed with Chore, Dathan, and Abiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is the bleſſed wyl of God, that the glorye of his militant churche ſhould multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie in perſecution, ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe vnder oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that out of the bloud of one catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:18721:21"/>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">ſufferinge deathe for Chriſte, ſhould aryſe manye holie chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> The bloud of the marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res (ſaith S. Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) is the ſeade of the churche, wherof aryſe and encreſe mo, as of the ſeede in the felde ſpringeth newe corne. The churche was amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites when they laye vnder the cruel bondage of Pharao, and of them it is written,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>The more they vvere oppreſſed, the more they increaſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.</note> The churche was but a litle flocke, when the fyrſt perſecution began at Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and yet ther of Chriſtes goſpel ſpred mightelie. It is Godes gracious gifte, that his churche ſhould proſper, when ſhe is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted.<note place="margin">Hila. de Triniitate lib <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> When ſhe is oppreſſed then ſhe is increaſed, when ſhe is iniured, then ſhe ouercometh, euen then ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quereth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſemeth to be ouercomed. The churche is lyke the palme tree, the greater waight is laide on it, the broder it ſpreadeth. The churche is lyke camomil, the
<pb facs="tcp:18721:21"/>
more you treade on it, the thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker it waxeth. It is written of the perſecuted.<note place="margin">Aug. de ciuitate lib. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> They were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, tyed in chaynes, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, killed, and torne in peeces, yet they encreaſed. The ſtorie mentioneth of a notable woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who hearinge that manye chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould be put to deathe, tooke hir childe in hir armes, ranne to profeſſe hir faithe, and to dye with them. The officer meetinge hir, demaunded whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe wente, ſhe tolde, hym to the place of the chriſtians. Why (ſayed he) they ſhal be al put to deathe. And I goo (quoth ſhe) to dye with them. But why (ſayed he) doeſt thou carye thy childe with thee? ſhe anſwered my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de <hi rend="margQuotes">ſhal take ſuche parte, as the mother doth. You that be nowe</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſted in the ſhippe of Chriſte, you that beare affliction for the churche of Chriſte, abide in the ſhippe, leape not oute, be not tipte ouer bourde, your gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours be ſure, ſkilful, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente
<pb facs="tcp:18721:22"/>
to ſaue you in al te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes, your twelue roers wil driue you into a ſafe porte, where no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of man, nor machination of diuel, ſhal ouertrowe you. You haue the helpe of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that gouerneth, you haue the promiſe of Chriſte his ſonne, that praieth, you haue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of the holie ghoſte, that ſtrengtheneth. God the father helpeth you, god the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne praieth for you, God the holie ghoſte ſtrengtheneth you. The holie Trinitie in one deitie gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you, and wil not leaue to giue you grace and fortitude to endure what affliction ſo euer, for the glorie of his holie name.</p>
            <p>Furthermore it ſhould be to you no litle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, to recogniſe the manifolde benefites, and bleſſinges of God, which you enioye, whiles you kepe your ſelues within the ſhippe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte. Chriſte hath but one ſhippe, that is one churche, one in vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:18721:22"/>
of faithe, one in vnitie of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, one in vnitie of ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, one in vnitie of head. They that be not of this one churche of this one faithe, vnder this one head, enioye not the healpe of the father, enioye not the prayer of the ſonne, nor the aſſiſtance of the holie ghoſte. To <hi rend="margQuotes">be of Chriſtes churche, in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes vnitie, is of ſuch importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that a conſtant chriſtian ſhoulde rather choſe to die, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aparte from it. It is no leſſe glorie to</hi> ſuffer martyrdome for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of vnitie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is,<note place="margin">Hiſt. eccl. li. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>34</hi>
               </note> not to offer to idolles, yea rather it is a greater martyrdome, for in the one, eache man ſuffereth for him ſelfe, in the other eache man ſuffereth for the whole churche. Now then you that be in vnitie, ſuffer for this vnitie, and chriſe happie be you, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god maketh worthie ſo to ſuffer. They that forſake the general faithe of Chriſtes churche, and truſte to ſome one article, leape out of the
<pb facs="tcp:18721:23"/>
ſhippe, and ſeme to catche at a litle bourde ther of. The bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge <hi rend="margQuotes">of any one article wil not ſaue vs, the not beleuinge of any one, wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne vs. They that</hi> forſake antiquitie, vniuerſalitie, conſente, and vnitie, enter into the ſtreames of ſchiſme, driue at the rocke of hereſie, whiuer vp and downe at euerie blaſte of doctrine, and populer flaterie, and ſhal neuer finde place of reſte, or quiet porte to arriue. Beholde, in how many greate perilles they be, whom this tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belous ſtorme hath ſhaken out of the ſhippe. Do they not endo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and haſarde their ſoules, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they enter into ſchiſme, and ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne out of ſchiſme into hereſie? As by ſchiſme they bereue them ſelues of charitie: ſo by hereſie they bereue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues of faithe. How can they ſeparat from the bodie, but they aparte alſo from the heade? They can hardelie diſmember them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche, and firmelie holde the
<pb facs="tcp:18721:23"/>
righte faithe, ſeinge faithe is the gifte of God, that floweth from Chriſte as from the heade, into his bodie and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres.  <hi rend="margQuotes">An eaſie leape it is out of ſchiſme into he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and as eaſie to procede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereſie to Apoſtaſie, for in here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie there is no ſtoppe, nor ſtaye.</hi> Scantlie ſhal you finde an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue heade that falleth into one hereſie, but ſlideth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to poynte into a multitude, vntil he diſlike euerie poynte of the catholike faithe, which poynte perdie is plaine Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from Apoſtaſie into Atheiſme, and Epicuriſme, the waye is made plaine. As then it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but comforte you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, that you kepe with in the ſhippe, out of ſchiſme in vnitie: ſo it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but recomforte you, that you be vnder vnitie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, in vnitie of faithe, that faithe which Chriſte preached, that faithe which his Apoſtles recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that faithe which the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worlde beleueth, that faithe
<pb facs="tcp:18721:24"/>
which our forefathers liued in, euen that Catholike Romaine faithe which now you liue in, and for which you ſuffer. Of this faithe you haue the righte ſenſe and felinge, when you hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Chriſte in the foundation, when you confeſſe the ſubſtance of Chriſtes doctrine vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by that holie ſpirite, which firſte penned it. Greate is the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your faithe, in al doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trines, in al ſacramentes, in al articles, and in al Apoſtolike and churchelie traditions. In obedience of this faithe, you beleue that Chriſtes worde is Chriſtes worke, and that by the mightie power of his word, he is made preſente with you, and geueth remiſſion and grace. In obedience of this faithe, you praye vnto Chriſtes ſainctes in heauen, you praye for Chriſtian ſoules in purgatorie, that they may praye for you in heauen. In obedience of this faithe, you grounde your hope, that God
<pb facs="tcp:18721:24"/>
wyl not leaue vnrewarded your prayers, your penance, your faſtinges, your almes, nor any good worke els what ſoeuer. When you ſuffer nowe for the general faithe of Chriſte, you ſuffer for euerie poynte, that chriſtian iuſtice bindeth you to confeſſe. And this is a ful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the faithe catholike, wherin you haue to acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the bleſſinges of God, that maketh you worthie to ſuffer for faithe, in obedience of faithe, for vnitie, in vnitie, for charitie in veritie. And here vpon haue you to muſe and meditate, when greefes recurre, that you ſuffer for the churche of Chriſte, and for the faithe of Chriſte with Chriſte, that ſuffered paineful deathe, to make his churche glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. They that be not of this churche, and of this faithe, be whithoute charitie,<note place="margin">Aug. li. <hi>2</hi> con. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con c. <hi>13</hi>
               </note> nor can they be pertakers of Godes charitie, which be enemies of his vnitie. Thoughe they receaue the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:18721:25"/>
of faithe, thoughe theire faithe be whole and ſounde, it doth not auaile them, ſo longe as ſoundnes of charitie, is killed with the dedlie wounde of ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,<note place="margin">Idem lib. <hi>1.</hi> contra D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. cap. <hi>8.</hi> Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tract. <hi>19.</hi> in euang. Ioan.</note> by whos onelie deathe, what euer thinges be ſounde of them ſelues, be drawen to dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. And ſchiſmatikes may doo good workes, but good workes doo not profite them. Thoughe they praye, thoughe they faſte,  <hi rend="margQuotes">thoughe they geue almes, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe they liue continent, thoughe they kepe virginitie, al doth not helpe, al doth not profite, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe they breake vnitie.</hi> Put to this, ſo longe as they be deuided from Chriſtes churche, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue not the life of his holie ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, <hi rend="margQuotes">for oute of his churche his holie ſpirite geueth not life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The churche is the myſtical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Chriſte, they muſt be of his bodie, that wil liue of his ſpirite.<note place="margin">Gregor. expla. <hi>5.</hi> Pſal. pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent.</note> Heretikes liue not of his ſpirite, ſchiſmatikes liue not of his ſpirite, excommunicat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:18721:25"/>
liue not of his ſpirite, and why? <hi rend="margQuotes">Becauſe they be not of his bodie. What lyfe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue they? they haue the lyfe of theire bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> but lacke the life of theire ſoules. they liue in their fleſhe, and die in their ſpirite, they die aliue. <hi rend="margQuotes">they liue without faithe, without charitie, without chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, without aulter, without prieſte, without ſacrifice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God.</hi> Conſider then the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable loſſe of them that bee leapte out of the ſhippe now in the time of this tempeſte. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the domage and dainger of them, which diſmember them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte and his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Schiſme bereueth them of vnitie and charitie, ſchiſme ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perareth them from Chriſte and his churche, ſchiſme ioyneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſynagoge of the diuel, ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me ſpoyleth them of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and grace. And where there is a communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of prayers, and of al good workes common to them that be vnited in Chriſte,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:26"/>
ſchiſme bereueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the frute of al prayers, of al good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and of al ſacrifices, finallie ſchiſme excludeth them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and leadeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hel. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, you that be of one vnitie in the houſe of God, beholde, what they leſe by ſchiſme, and ſee what you gaine by vnitie. You (I ſaye) that be in the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of Chriſte, you that be confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant catholikes, al you that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the catholike vnitie, let your comfortes encreaſe to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de thes bleſſinges of God, to wyt that you be of one faithe, of one charitie, of one churche, of one vnitie, vnder one heade, that you be of the communion of ſainctes, that you be perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of ſanctification, of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and grace, that you be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of al good workes done in the whole chriſtian worlde, of al ſacrifices, of al prayers, of al penance, of al faſtinges, and of what els ſoeuer be done in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal churche of Chriſte, and
<pb facs="tcp:18721:26"/>
that in the ende, you be ſure to be pertakers of Chriſtes deathe and merites, which is al that you labour for, when now you beare the croſſe of Chriſte. And for what thinge ſoeuer God per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitteth you preſentlie to beare his croſſe, (his iudgementes be ſecrete,) in effecte you ſuffer on the croſſe, which thinge muſt be your comforte. <hi rend="margQuotes">For yf you ſuffer for your ſinnes, you ſuffer vpon the croſſe of the good thefe. If you ſuffer for iuſtice ſake (as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringe for religion you can not but ſuffer for iuſtice) then may you take more comforte therof, becauſe you ſuffer vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtes owne croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what yf the profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the churche nickename you? What yf they reuile you? yea what yf they hate you? The coniunction of ſoules vnited in God, the diſlikinge of ſpirites aparted from God is ſuch,<note place="margin">Cypr. ad Quir. de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib. <hi>1.</hi> piſt. <hi>3.</hi> ib. <hi>4.</hi> piſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that their can be no entier likinge,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:27"/>
nor louinge alia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the and infidelitie, truthe and falſehood, lighte and darkenes, Antechriſte and Chriſte. They that breake charitie, wil not like of you that kepe vnitie, nor wil they commende you, that be gon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you. The diuel (that is auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of diuiſion,) is alwayes ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe againſte the vnited mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſte. It is his tricke to blemiſhe and abaſe, to infame and obſcure the glorious name of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that be of better note and conuerſation, to the ende they mighte finde leſſe reputation, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the worlde. Porphirius was a reuiler of chriſtians,<note place="margin">Hiſt. eccl. lib <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> and a rayler at their religion. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he could not finde oughte that he might iuſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende in Origenes commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, he began to nickename him, and to rayſe at his perſon. In like maner doth the partie proteſtante, miſlikinge with the catholike cauſe, and with the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike onelie for the cauſe, bein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:18721:27"/>
inſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to anſwere theire matter, nickename theire per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes, that they mighte make them odious by reprocheful na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and falſe intended crimes. What ado make they, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they chapter (as they doo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monlie,) vpon the names of Rome, pope and papiſte? How rappe they oute theire railinge rhetorike, when they heare the conſented doctrine of Chriſtes churche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged? As they diſcourſe ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelie, and make a populer ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of ſugered wordes conninge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſo yet when al is ſaide, the ſomme of theire drifte is, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke their rouinge aduantage, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the names of Rome, Pope, and papiſtrie. And what els do they ſaye in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſte the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued doctrines of the churche, but that the beleuers be papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and the doctrines papiſtrie. As it may be, that a good natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red man wolde ſhonne a contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious ſpeache: ſo it ſhould not greue a right enformed catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:18721:28"/>
that liueth in the feare of God, and in the faithe of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des churche, to be reproched by the vngodlye, which haue no feare, nor faithe, no remorſe what God ſeeth, nor what the worlde ſayeth. As for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of papiſte, and papiſtrie, they bringe in dede with them a preiudice amonge the children of the worlde, and were inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the firſte founders of the fifth goſpel, to bringe religion in contempte, and to make the <hi rend="margQuotes">catholike odious, wheras in truthe thes names be not infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous by diriuation, but by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious interpretation.</hi> It ſhould not greatelie moue an vnderſtandinge chriſtian, to be called papiſte, for yf he conſider a principal grounde of our chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, <hi rend="margQuotes">he can not be a ſaued chriſtian, that is not a pure pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſte.</hi> In the beginninge of the goſpel,<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. <hi>3.</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ict. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpirit. <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> chriſtians began to be odious, euen then they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled, mocked, called fooles, and
<pb facs="tcp:18721:28"/>
witleſſe folke, becauſe they folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed Chriſte. Euen then they were ſpoyled, and al that would iniurie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mighte make theire praye of them. It may come to paſſe againe in the reuolution of a fewe yeares, that the name of a chriſtian, wil be as odious with the Machiauelian, that vſeth religion but for a polecie, as nowe is the name of papiſte with the proteſtante, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to any religion. As odious was the chriſtian name ſome nomber of yeares after Chriſte, as nowe is the name of papiſte, and as muche malice did the enemies of chriſtianitie worke againſte the knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, whom they called ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finglie <hi>Chriſticolas,</hi> to wit worſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hipers of Chriſte, as now the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of Chriſtes churche wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke againſte the catholikes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cal odiouſlie <hi>Papiſtas,</hi> to wit ſuch as ſhewe their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the pope, that is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes vicar, Peters ſucceſſor,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:29"/>
the highe preeſte, and heade byſhoppe of the whole chriſtian worlde. You be the children of the churche, you be the children of vnitie, yf you be nickenamed for dewties ſake where dewtie is dewe, that is oute of courſe, and blame worthie in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſo name you. But the caſe beinge as it is remedileſſe, the ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Chriſte muſte holde them ſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente to ſuffer tearmes, and tauntes, raylinges, and reproches, ſeinge Chriſte their lorde and maiſter, coulde not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11</note> Was not Chriſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled with opprobrious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, importinge ſhame and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne? Was he not ſaide to be a freinde to publicans and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Was he not called Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan? and albeit there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer founde in him exceſſe, yet they called him a wyne bibber, and a man of meate aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Yea they lefte not his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine workes vntouched, in them alſo they ſaide he wroughte by a
<pb facs="tcp:18721:29"/>
diuel, and the prince of diuelles.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.</note> When they coulde not abide his doctrine, for his doctrines ſake, they glaunced at his perſon. It can not be defended but you be ſynners. But what ſynne is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the name of papiſte? Doubtles none at al, but that vnder this name, they woulde make odious not onelie your perſonnes, but your faithe and religion, which is that onelie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi rend="margQuotes">and faithe, of whos com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion whoſoeuer be not, be not of Chriſtes faithe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Amonge vs that be in baniſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te,</hi> it is counted more irkeſome in thes rebellious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes, to be forced from coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie to countrie, from ſtate to ſtate, to be ſacked, to finde penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and in euerie parte to ſee a feareful face of miſerie, then to heare a fewe ſyllables, and them not of yl ſounde nother, yf they bee wel taken. Wordes be often as they be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and as the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, that ſpeake them.
<pb facs="tcp:18721:30"/>
S. Peter and the diuel vſed like wordes,<note place="margin">Auguſt. tract <hi>6.</hi> in epiſt. Ioan. Ioan. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte to be the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God. Chriſte aſked the Iewes for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſoughte, they anſwered, for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth. Their wordes were good, theire meaninge yl. The Iewes mocked Chriſte, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſaluted him thus, <hi>Aue rex iudaeorum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 27</note> The chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s honor him with the ſame wordes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they knele downe and ſaye, <hi>Aue rex, &amp;c.</hi> Wordes that may haue good meaninge, ſhould not offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de good meaninge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thoughe miſcrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes miſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Should we not abide the worde <hi>Galilaea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Triper. li. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> for that Iulianus Apoſtata ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte oute a tauntinge blaſphemie againſt Chriſt, what time he cried out <hi>viciſti Galilaee,</hi> thou of Galilee haſt ouercomed? Or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he called the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, men of Galilee?<note place="margin">Triper li. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> Should we haue leſſe reuerent opinion of Chriſte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that vnhappie man Felix treaſeror to Iulianus, called Chriſte Maries ſonne, vſinge
<pb facs="tcp:18721:30"/>
thes wordes? <hi>Ecce quibus vaſis Mariae filio miniſtratur.</hi> Aſee in what veſſelles they ſerue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. Or ſhoulde we forſake the faithe of Chriſtes deitie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantialitie with God his father, becauſe the Aria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s called the catholikes <hi>Homouſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s?</hi> what reproches, calu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, and ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders the enemies of Chriſte inuented againſte the chriſtians, the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelie ſtories beare witneſſe, but yf you marke who they were that reproched Chriſte, and who they be that nowe nickename the chriſtians, you ſhal ſee litle cauſe to be offended, but rather cauſe to praye, that they may be ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.<note place="margin">Hiero in proc dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo aduer. Pelag.</note> To good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath not ben greuous, to haue the diſple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the euil. As for diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of heretikes, good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſought it, and thought glorie to' beare it.<note place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſt. <hi>80.</hi>
               </note> S. Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> endeuored to' make the enemies of the churche his enemies, and wrought to S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it was his glorie to be deteſted of heretikes. How much
<pb facs="tcp:18721:31"/>
they deteſte your honor, your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and your perſonnes, it is apparente when they blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me your religion, cal you papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, rebelles, and treitors. But this their demeanor maketh good your cauſe and renoumeth your perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes,<note place="margin">Grego. li. <hi>1.</hi> ſuper Eze bo. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the good. For then doth there appeare ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me euident iuſtice in you, when you diſpleaſe them, that pleaſe not God. No man can be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi rend="margQuotes">to almightie God, and to his enemies in the ſame thinge.</hi> For he denyeth hym ſelfe a freinde to God, that pleaſeth his enemie. And it may be feared leſt they that blemyſhe the good partes of deuoure chriſtians, (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they can not charge but for religion, which in dede is Godes parte,) wyl fal as far oute with God, yf his grace te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per not their defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. hom. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> in Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Cain maligned his brother Abel, and therwith contemned God. Ioſephes brothers regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hym not, and they regarded God as litle. The children of
<pb facs="tcp:18721:31"/>
Iſrael reiected Moyſes, and in hym they reiected God. It is ſayde to be a machiauelian po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to terrifie the vntowarde and recuſante parte, with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius termes of rebel and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, when greate purpoſes be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. Though it can not be but greuous to a true meaninge man that is of ciuile loialtie, to be preſſed with termes of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crimes not at al intended, and that for his dewe ſeruice to God: yet ſhould not this pointe infirme the confeſſion of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante catholike, that feareth God aboue al, knowinge that it hath ben proper to tyrannycal <hi rend="margQuotes">ſtates in tymes of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to alter the worſhepers of Chriſte, by terrours and tormentes, to terrifie the deuoute chriſtians with word and ſworde, therbye to wynne them to theire purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, therbye to make them indue theire affections, to loue and to hate what they loued or hated, or els to haue no quietnes.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede
<pb facs="tcp:18721:32"/>
we be neyther rebelles nor traitors to princes, yf we leaue vndone the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of the prince, and do the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God. When Daniel praied thriſe adaye to God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the kinges commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched contrarie to the willes of the rulers, it was neyther trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor were they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles or traitors. Thoughe the rage of the rulers go ſo farre as to caſte vs to the ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte Daniel, thoughe they whippe vs, as they wipped the Apoſtels, wee muſt ſuffer with Daniel, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſaye with the Apoſtles, we muſte rather obeye God in doinge our dewtie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man forbiddinge the ſame. And what is our comforte herein, but that god hath wayes enoughe to deliuer vs, as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered Daniel, as he deliuered the Apoſtles, or els wil ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen vs to die in his quarel, whether ſhal be more for his glorie, and the edefyinge of his holie chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. But let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hate you, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:18721:32"/>
cal you what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liſteth for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente to beare, it is godes cauſe, it is Chriſtes qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rel, leaue to him the reuenge. Yf you were giltie of that viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which opened the waye to a ruffia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>like ruſhinge into al vice, yf you were giltie of a monſterous maſſe of tragecal treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yf you ſowed ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at home, or maintained rebellion abrode, yf hauinge no churche at home to robbe, you ſought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries adioynin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to robbe churches, to breake images, to be hange men to the images of Chriſt and our ladie, to diſmount aulters, to kyl prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to defile with prophane handes the pretious bodie and bloud of our ſauiour Chriſt in the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the aulter, yf (I ſay) you were giltie of thes horrible factes, and in this reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte they called you heretikes, traitors, churche robbers, and murtherers, ſurelie then you ſhould not be offended, for ſuch factes, deſerue ſuche names.
<pb facs="tcp:18721:33"/>
And thes names perdie importe muche more, and be of greater conſequence, then the termes of papiſte, and papiſtrie. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you folowe not theire cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe which forſake the highe waye, and vnder the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes croſſe, haue ſo croſſed the waye, broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe the hedges, trodde downe ſo muche good corne, and ſo manie faire paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of pietie, that except they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me backe, they can neuer come to God. Becauſe (I ſaye) you fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe not this courſe of proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, they afflicte you by al poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes, they perſecute you with wordes, they perſecute you with ſwordes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note>You haue not receaued the ſpirite of the worlde, but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite which is of God. Yf the worlde hate you, Chriſte our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de loueth you. Harken what our lorde ſaithe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>If the vvorlde hate you, you knovve that it hated me before, yf you vvere of the vvorl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:33"/>
the vvorlde vvolde loue his ovvne. Becauſe you be not of the vvorlde, but I haue choſen you oute of the vvorlde, therfore the vvorlde hateth you. The ſeruant is not greater then the lorde, yf they haue perſecuted me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>they vvil alſo perſecute you. Bleſſed be you vvhen they ſhal curſe you, and perſecute you, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhal ſaye al yl againſt you, makinge lies of you for my ſake, be you glad and reioyſe, becauſe your revvarde is greate in heauen, for ſo haue they perſecuted the prophetes, that vvere before you.</hi> And why did the worlde hate our lorde, that came for loue to ſaue the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de? This ſaieth our lorde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>The vvorlde hateth me, becauſe I teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that the vvorkes of the vvorl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be yl.</hi> Here may I ſaye, and trulie ſaye, that yf hereſie be a ſpiritual idolatrie, yf ſchiſme he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and blaſphemie be nowe the workes of the worlde, then ſurelie the worlde hateth you, becauſe you teſtifie that the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes
<pb facs="tcp:18721:34"/>
of the worlde be yl, you te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie in your faithe, you teſtifie in your life. Why were you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refte of dignities, offices, liuele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and libertie? Why be you in bondes and bondage, in pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonmente, and baniſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? why be you yet diſplaced, abaſed, and defaced in the worlde? I ſpeake vnto you, o you worthie confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſante catholikes, that lie at home in chaines, and feede on the noyſome ayres, of vnſauerie priſonnes. I ſpeake vnto you that haue ſuffered a longe, and lingeringe martyrdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,<note place="margin">Cip lib. <hi>2</hi> epist. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and ſtil do ſuffer paineful fighte not ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les you bee daylie crowned, the longer you fighte, the more is your victorie, the greater is your rewarde. And you that beare aboute you your paineful endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to whom al your countrie is but a priſon, and you that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue your heartes wrapped in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines to ſee religion abandoned, to ſe godes honor contemned, to
<pb facs="tcp:18721:34"/>
ſee Godes ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes puniſhed, al you do teſtifie, that the workes of the worlde be yl. Repoſe you therfore your comforte in God, his workes be righte, he diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth al thinges ſweetelie, and worketh to good ende. He per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth not you to ſuffer for his cauſe but to the ende you mighte take profite of it, and ſuche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, as tendeth to the healthe of your ſoules. In this ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you can not but take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte in the equitie of your cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, againſte which men haue no more power then God geueth, no more then God permitteth, for al power is of God. Yf God permitte euil men to plage the good, that turneth to theire comforte, yf they conſider,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> that God worketh good of theire yl, and ſuffereth the euil to liue ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be amended, or that the good by them mighte be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed. God dealeth with you as the angrye father dealeth with his childe, whom after he
<pb facs="tcp:18721:35"/>
hath beaten, caſteth the rodde into the fire,<note place="margin">Idem in Pſal. <hi>73.</hi>
               </note> maketh muche of him, and leaueth to him his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie. <hi rend="margQuotes">It is godes ordinarie mercie, to inſtructe the good by the euil, and to experciſe thoſe that ſhal be ſaued, by the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral power of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſhal be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned.</hi> In this exerciſe this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, that he vſeth euil men but for a tyme, as the father vſeth the rodde to beate his childe. This is the comforte, ſuch as be nowe called <hi>flagella Dei,</hi> ſuche as be puniſhers and perſecutors of goddes people, haue but theire time, in the ende they be caſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire, as Pharao was, as Herod was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.</note> as Aſſur was, of whom it is ſaide, <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Aſſur the rodde of my furie.</hi> The churche hath nowe hir Pharaos, hir Aſſurs, and hir Herodes, which be the roddes and whippes of Godes people.</hi> God wil caſte thes rod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des alſo into the fire, for he is bothe merciful and iuſte, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge their malicious machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:35"/>
and ſeinge theire wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes againſte the throne of his maieſtie, againſt the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>althe of his holie churche, he wil trippe them in their turne, and turne them into the fire, in good time. This ſaith our lorde. <hi>The reuenge is myne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32</note> 
               <hi>I vvil ſo paye them in tyme, as they ſhal faile of theire ſtandinge.</hi> Ariſe o lorde in time, let al the kinges of the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the feare thy name.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Ariſe and haue mercie vpon Sion, for it is time to haue mercie vpon hir, pea the time is come. There is riſen a great tempeſte in the ſea, thy ſhippe is couered with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, thy churche is ſore afflicted.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 13 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> The enemie ſoweth darnel in the lande of our lorde. Belial would haue felowſhippe with Chriſte,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4</note> Alexander the coper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmyth doth the ſainctes muche yl. What ſhal I ſaye?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 27</note> Barrabas is lowſed, Chriſt is bounde, the lawes be chainged, catholikes that now be afflicted for iuſtice ſake, ſuffer by lay lawes ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:18721:36"/>
puniſhementes, as traitors and heretikes ſuffered, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lawes were in place.<note place="margin">Auguſt. epiſt. <hi>48</hi> Vincent.</note> But recomforte here your afflicted ſpirites, o you afflicted catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, conſider you the difference of the cauſe in ſufferinge. When good and euil men do the ſame thinges, and ſuffer the ſame paynes, they are not to be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by their doinges or ſufferin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but by the cauſes, why they ſo doo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.</note> or ſuffer, marke the point. Pharao afflicted godes people with greuous labours. Here the perſecutor was a wicked man, the perſecuted were the people of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32</note> Moyſes afflicted the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me people for their diſobedience againſte God and him. Here the perſecutor was a good man, the people perſecuted were euil. Pharao and Moyſes dyd the like thinges, bothe afflicted the people, but bothe had not like purpoſe, and entention. The one afflicted with tyrannical affection to oppreſſe them, the
<pb facs="tcp:18721:36"/>
other puniſhed with charitable zeale, to amende them. Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blablie Ieſabel ſlewe the true prophetes of God.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18</note> Elias ſlewe the falſe prophetes of Baal. Chriſte whiype the Iewes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2. <hi>Idem</hi> 19</note> the Iewes whipped Chriſte. The Apoſtles were deliuered to the power of men to be puniſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> the Apoſtles deliuered me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the power of the diuel to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. In good times when God was feared, and the churche la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes reuerenced, catholikes pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed heretikes, nowe hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes perſecute catholikes. In this ſimilitude of puniſhemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, the cauſe of puniſhemente is to be diſcerned, and ſo be the mindes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be puniſhers, for the puniſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te may be like, yet the cauſe vnlike, the puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente one, the cauſe not one. In the cauſe this is to be noted who be the doers, who be the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, who do for iuſtice and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, who ſuffer for ſynne and iniquitie, who do to hinder,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:37"/>
and who do to profite. Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wene the churche of Chriſte, and the ſynagoge of the diuel, this is the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the churche afflicteth for loue, the ſynagoge for hatred. the churce to correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, the ſynagoge to deiecte, the one to reuoke from error, the other to prouoke into error.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra corrected Agar hir maide, that fledde from hir, and was willed by the Angel to returne. In Agar ſchiſmatikes and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes be repreſented,<note place="margin">Auguſt. epist. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> who ſet them ſelues proudelie againſte the churche, that is theire mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris and mother, and therfore be corrected by hir, that after they be made humble by holſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me diſcipline, they mighte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to hir. Our lorde geueth a manifeſte note, how to diſcerne them that ſuffer for his ſake, wher he ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug li. <hi>1</hi> de ſermo in Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed be they that ſuffer perſecution for iuſtice ſake, becauſe theirs is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</hi> When he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>For iuſtice ſake,</hi> comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge
<pb facs="tcp:18721:37"/>
them that ſo ſuffer with the promis of his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lye kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedome, heretikes be excluded from this rewarde, becauſe they ſuffer not <hi>propter iuſtitiam,</hi> for iuſtice. Where there is not a ſound faithe, there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, for the iuſte man liueth by faithe. Nor can ſchiſmatikes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye this reward, becauſe where there is not charitie, there can not bee iuſtice. When therfore the doers do like, and the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers ſuffer like, wee muſt diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the mindes of them that be doers, and the cauſe of them that be ſufferers. Certaine it is, that bothe good and euil do ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me tyme afflicte, vſe the like pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhementes, and pretende the ſame cauſe, euen the cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. The difference is, bothe do it not in like order, with one minde, nor to one ende. In the cauſe of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the good afflicte the euil by cenſures and churche lawe to repreſſe diuiſion, to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe error, and to ſaue veritie.
<pb facs="tcp:18721:38"/>
The euil afflicte the good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt lawe and order, to ſerue their intended purpoſe, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre their faction, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hereſie. In the cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the good afflict the euil, for diſobedience and breache of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the euil afflicte the good, for kepinge obedience, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge with iuſtice. And here in the name of iuſtice is implied truthe of doctrine, which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in inward belefe, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion. And this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion may be eyther in wordes or in workes, ſo that who ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth for any facte wherbye he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth the faithe, and beareth witnes of Chriſte, ſuffereth for truthe and iuſtice.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.</note> So dyd Iohn Baptiſt ſuffer, ſo do they nowe ſuffer, that be perſecuted for the catholike cauſe, they that be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted for ſeruinge of god, they that ſaye Maſſe, they that heare Maſſe, brefelie al they that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the confeſſion of Chriſtes churche, ſuffer for iuſtice. You
<pb facs="tcp:18721:38"/>
therfore o you perſecuted catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, to you I ſpeake againe, you directelie ſuffer for iuſtice ſake. You abide by it, you ſtande in the face of the perſecutors, to you belongeth the promis of Chriſte, yours is the kingedome of heauen. You glorious confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, what honor ſhoulde Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte haue nowe in our miſerable countrie, yf you were not open co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſors of his honor? You ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this affliction for his honor, you ſuffer for the honor of his ſainctes, you ſuffer for the honor of his ſacramentes, you ſuffer for the honor of the vniuerſal churche. You bleſſed ſufferers, endure you to ſuffer ſo longe as God woulde you to ſuffer, and bleſſed be you that ſuffer, for yours is the kingedome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>And you afflicted catholikes, you that lie and liue as ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſcattered in diſperſion, to you nowe I ſpeake, you leeſe not
<pb facs="tcp:18721:39"/>
the name of confeſſors. Many of you ſtode in the firſte fronte of the fighte, and confeſſed your dewtiful obedience before the face of the maieſtrate. Many of you fledde without preiudice, but not withoute minde to fight againe. You haue ben afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by degrees, you haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced oute of your countrie, into this countrie, where in time you were brought oute of credite by them, that wiſhed you wel ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at home nor abrode. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies were made, terrible trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes contriued, the factious parte rebelled, and nowe began<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ciuil and vnnatural warre. What ouertwhartes fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wee, into how many ſuſpitions ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne wee, What obloquies, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of treaſon ſuſtained wee, that mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not vniuſtlie? If wee looke to the common trobles of thes countries, they haue not be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to this people, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and perſonal to vs. The ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kage and ſpoyles which the gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:18721:39"/>
deſerued, fel vpon vs that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued them not. Wee haue ben greued not onelie by the hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, whos treaſons wee miſliked, but by the catholike alſo, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee fledde to be releued. And wee haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo greued by bothe, that neceſſitie forced to chainge our place, hardelye were wee ſuffered to remaine in place, and not without troble in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer place. Thy iudgementes (o lorde) be ſecrete, thy mercies be greate, to thee we muſt ſinge mercie and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, for thou haſt kepte vs, and ſtil doeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte vs, in thes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinewed tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. O you holie fathers and Monkes of Scheme, o you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute brothers and virgins of Sion, you prelates and prieſtes, you lordes and ladies, and you that be of pope Gregories fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſeminaries at Rome, and Reimes, the riſinge helpe and hope of your decayed countrie, al you of what note ſo euer you bee, that be baniſhed catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:40"/>
and beare affliction for the catholike cauſe, al you do teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to the worlde, that the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the worlde be yl, al you reporte to good mennes conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in open truthe, that you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for iuſtice ſake. How many of you were at home in good ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and place to ſerue God, and your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie? But when Godes honor was diſplaced, you choſe to relinquiſhe al, and to truſte to his holie prouidence. You that haue enioyed muche worldlie proſperitie, refuſe not nowe to ſuſtaine aduerſitie, and to ſaye with holie Iob.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Dominus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp;c. our lorde gaue it, our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hath taken it avvaye, bleſſed be the name of our lorde.</hi> What euer the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of the worlde be, it is no ſyn to be in baniſhment, it is no ſhame to be poore for Chriſtes ſake.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Better is the poore that liueth barelie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ritche man that walketh cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedlie. And better is a litle with the feare of God, then greate
<pb facs="tcp:18721:40"/>
treaſures without his feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humiliation is the chriſtian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iacob.</hi> 1.</note> therfore is the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willed to reioyſe in it. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is broughte to be poore, when he is made an outecaſt not repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he muſt reioyſe in pouertie, in ignomie, and in preſſure, for thes be the exaltations of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, thes be the prefermentes of ſainctes, who be exalted of God, when they be contemned of the worlde. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte is, that God maketh them poore in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to make them ritche in faithe, the comforte is, that our lorde leaueth them not hopeleſſe. This ſaith our lorde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 41.</note> 
               <hi>Probaui te in camino paupertatis.</hi> I haue tried thee, in the fornai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of pouertie. It is often ſene, that our lorde taketh from his freindes the worldelie partes and pelfe wherin they truſted, that they might put their whole truſte in him. What ſoeuer God hath taken from vs, yet hath he not lefte vs deſtitute, ſuch is his
<pb facs="tcp:18721:41"/>
merciful prouidence.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> Wee be in pouertie, but not vtterlie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ſomwhat, we be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but not forſaken, we be caſte downe, yet we periſhe not. God gaue vs liuinges, ſome in one degree, ſome in an other. Some had muche, ſome had litle, <hi rend="margQuotes">al had inoughe. How muche be we al bounde to render daylie than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vnto God, who of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes voucheſafed to geue vs ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, that we mighte leeſe for his ſake.</hi> Let vs confeſſe in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des name, the recheleſneſſe wee had of Godes houſe, and the ouermuche care wee had of the worlde. God knewe vs to be wantonnes, and farre ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne out of that courſe of righteouſnes, which our holie fathers had in Chriſtes churche. Yet doth he not beat vs cruellie as he might of iuſtice, but hydeeth the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reful ſcourge of his greuous correction, and ſheweth the ſofte rodde of his ſweete diſcipline. Bleſſed be the name of God,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:41"/>
that aduerſitie hath opened our eies, which proſperitie had ſhut. And bleſſed be his name againe and againe, that we may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſaye. <hi>Our lorde is at hande.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Our lorde is our helper at our nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and in our tribulation.</hi> We may iuſtlie ſaye,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Virga tua &amp; ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus tuus: &amp;c. Thy rodde and thy ſtaffe hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted me.</hi> Thoughe God beate vs with his rodde, yet he beareth vs vp with his ſtaffe. He beateth vs with the rodde of his outwarde correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and gideth vs with the ſtaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of his inwarde direction, the direction of the holie ghoſt who in our correction directeth vs, geueth vs grace and ſtrengthe to beare, that we murmure not, nor deſpaire in affliction. As for baniſhement why ſhould we thinke it puniſhement, ſeinge al the worlde is but a baniſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, al the worlde is but a citie of puniſhementes and dwellinge place of wretched me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye chriſtian can not be baniſhed
<pb facs="tcp:18721:42"/>
from Chriſte wher euer he be, <hi rend="margQuotes">in Chriſte there is no banyſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and without Chriſte al is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhement.</hi> But yf this banyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement be a puniſhement, yet doth God turne it to our bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. If it be a puniſhement to lacke our countrie (which is now the countrie of deuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſchiſme) yet is it our benefite to be where we may lyue in vnitie, wher we may ſerue God open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and confeſſe our faithe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Yf it be a puniſhement to lacke the companie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of our freindes, yet is it our benefite to be out of the companie of ſchiſmatikes and heretikes. God commaunded Moyſes to wil his people to departe from the tabernacles of Chore and his complices, who wer ſwalowed into the earthe aliue, for the ſynne of ſchiſme. Who knoweth not that the verie place of ſchiſme and hereſie, hath in it a ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Who knoweth not that
<pb facs="tcp:18721:42"/>
the common corruption of the time breadeth dulnes of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wher ther is no open ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of pietie. Yea the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge vndone of deuoute vſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the diſcontinuance from ſeinge and hearinge of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actes, worketh inſenſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of ſynne. How many good folkes liue now where hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes beare the ſwaye, out of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and hearinge of catholike religion, which deſire to ſee and heare, what we ſee and heare? For alas, what dayes ſee they? what threates heare they? In what trobles be they? what lacke of vnitie, what loſſe of charitie finde they? Were there no outeward perſecution, yet is this an inwarde perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to heare the diſorders, and to ſee the outrages of euil men. What an exerciſe is it to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, to liue amonge vnciuil proteſtantes, to liue amonge ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, as be not ſo litle as hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. What a coraze is it to heare
<pb facs="tcp:18721:43"/>
their blaſphemous wordes, and to ſee their ſhamles workes? What man that is of any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſenſe, or catholike zeale, can heare with patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eares Godes anointed prieſt and prince of his people, to be called Antechriſt? Chriſtes ſainctes to be diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Chriſtes ſacramentes to be contemned, and Chriſtes holie name to be blaſphemed? To the good and godlie, this is a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,<note place="margin">Auguſt. epist. ad Sebast.</note> thoughe there were no other perſecution. For what doth ſo perſecute the good, as the lyfe and maners of the euil? Now an perſecuted Loth when he liued amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the Sodomites,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Pet. cap. <hi>2.</hi> Auguſt ſer <hi>24.</hi> de verb. apoſt.</note> but makinge his abode amonge vnclene, proude, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous liuers, he ſuffered perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not in ſufferinge any puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, but in hearinge and ſeinge that which was yl. To catholikes which be in this caſe, this may be ſaide. Thoughe it be a greuous exerciſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge euil liuers, yet may good
<pb facs="tcp:18721:43"/>
men ſo doo without mayme of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie. It is a holie heuines,<note place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſt. ad Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt.</note> and (yf it may be ſo called) a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie miſerie, to be trobeled (ſo you be not intangeled) with other mens vices. This is the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution that al men ſuffer, which wyl liue holelie in Chriſte. It is not ſo commendable to be good with the good, but to be good amonge the euil.<note place="margin">Grego. <hi>1.</hi> ca lib <hi>1.</hi> in Iob. Iob. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> Iob that liued in the lande of gentiles, ſaieth of hym ſelfe. <hi>I haue ben a companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and a felovve of Oſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> The prophet ſaith.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faithleſſe people, and renegates be in thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, thou dvvelleſt amonge ſcorpions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> The Philippians liued in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of a croked and peruerſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet S. Paule willed them to be <hi>fauteles, and to ſhyne as lightes in the vvorlde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.</note> It was ſaide to them that were of the churche of Pargamos, <hi>I knovve thy vvorkes and vvhere thou dvvelleſt, euen vvhere ſathanas ſeate is, yet doeſt thou kepe my
<pb facs="tcp:18721:44"/>
name, and haſt not denied my faithe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grego. in Iob. lib. <hi>20.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> He refuſeth to be an Abel, that wil not abyde Cains ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce. In one barne lyeth corne and ſtrawe, in the threſhinge flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wre, the corne is troden vnder the ſtrawe. Doo we not ſee in the feldes, flowres growinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge brambles? Euenſo mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſynners be ioyned with the iuſte, and they be approued good, which endure good amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the euil. But to returne to vs that liue in banyſhemente, in that wee be departed from thoſe tabernacles, and from the felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe of thoſe ſchiſmatikes, in that we now liue out of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, in a countrie where we liue in Chriſtes vnitie, this is our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, and this is our comforte, that God turneth this tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral punyſhement, to our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual benefit. I am no prophet nor the ſonne of a prophet, yet for that wee profeſſe the faithe of the prophetes, the faithe of the Apoſtles, and the auncient
<pb facs="tcp:18721:44"/>
catholike Romaine faithe, for that we ſtande in the diſgrace and indignation of them, by whoſe lawes we were depriued of our liuinges, and lyke to be depriued of our liues alſo, had wee not fledde, I doute not but God that fed the prophet Elias when he fledde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſabel, wil feede vs alſo, for other cauſe wee had none to flee, but for Godes cauſe onelie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.</note> Wee fledde as Moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes fledde out of Egipte, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of Pharao.<note place="margin">3 <hi>Reg.</hi> 17</note> Wee fledde as Elias fledde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Achab and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabel. Wee fledde as Chriſte byd vs into an other citie. Nowe in what place or caſe ſo euer wee bee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.</note> 
               <hi>See that vve put our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God, and he vvil bringe to naughte ſuche as trobble vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee that haue ſuffered, and ſtil do ſuffer for ſo iuſte, ſo noble, and ſo honorable a cauſe as reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is, may not be diſmayed with the trobles of the worlde. God calleth by the rodde of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:45"/>
and by the mercies of his conſolation. It is the righte courſe and directe way wheroye God calleth his freindes to him, to beginne with them in tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The hope of the one, is the comforte in the other, and a ſoueraigne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte it is to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that the thinges which be trobelous paſſe awaye, the thinges which be glorious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for euer. Therfore is the tribulation of this worlde cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led lighte, not in reſpecte of the qualitie of tribulation, but in reſpecte of the wil,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> the hope and the rewarde of them that throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe tribulation contende to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Who is ignorante, but God declareth a ſinguler loue towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12</note> whom he correcteth. <hi>VVhom he loueth, he correcteth, and beateth euerie ſonne, vvhom he receaueth.</hi> And why doth he correcte but to amende vs? Why wolde he ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs,<note place="margin">Aug. ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>46.</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> but to make vs worthie of him. We haue therfore cauſe to reioyſe in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:45"/>
for yf we be iuſte, then be we tryed, yf we be vniuſte, then be we amended. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the worlde do maruel, why God ſo dealeth with his freindes, why he abaſeth them ſo greatelie in this worlde, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he choſe ſo highelie before the worlde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 3.</note> God commended his faitheful ſeruant Iob, by the teſtimonie of his owne mouthe. Yet was he broughte to ſuche abaſemente, that him ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned his calamitous caſe, and doleful dayes vpon a dungehil. Were not the prophetes and ſainctes of the olde teſtamente perſecuted?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>tried vvith mockin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, vvith ſcourginges, vvith pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment? vvere they not ſtoned, hevven aſunder, and ſlaine vvith ſvvorde? vvalked not they vp and dovvne deſtitute and trobeled? dyd they not vvander in vvilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in mountaines, in dennes and caues of the earthe? they vvould not be deliuered of theire troble, that they might inherite a better
<pb facs="tcp:18721:46"/>
reſurrection.</hi> Euen ſo it fel to the Apoſtles and ſainctes of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we teſtamente,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>VVhom God ſet forthe for the lovveſt of al, as men appointed to deathe, as men that vvere made gaſinge ſtockes to the vvorlde, as men that vvere fooles for Chriſtes ſake, men that vvere naked, hungred, thriſted, and had no certaine dvvellinge place, men that vvere accounted the filthe and ſcouringe of the vvorlde.</hi> Amonge the children of women there was not a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Iohn Baptiſte yet was he impriſoned, and done to dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. It is godes ordinarie mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, firſte to amende his children by correction, and after to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from damnation. <hi rend="margQuotes">And in this life God ſpareth the wicked, and not the electe, in the life to come, he ſpareth the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and not the wicked. He ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to be broughte to the loweſt, becauſe he ſeeth how to aduaunce them in the higheſte. He deiecteth them oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardelie
<pb facs="tcp:18721:46"/>
euen to contempte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he bringeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inwardlie, to thinges incomprehenſible.</hi> Yf God thus afflicte them whom he hath choſen and loueth, what are they like to ſuffer, whom he doth hate and reprobate? The prophet toke it for Godes good bleſſinge, that he was made humble by tribulation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118</note> This he ſaith, <hi>It is good for me that thou haſt humbled me, before I vvas corrected, I ſinned.</hi> And he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth further in the perſon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ſeke of God to be aſſayed in this worlde by tribulation. <hi>Proue me o lorde, aſſaye me, burne my raynes, and my hearte.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.</note> It was S. Auſtin that ſaide, <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Hic vre, hic ſeca, vt in eternum parcas.</hi> Cut me here, ſeare me here, that thou mayeſt ſpare me for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Albeit holie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liue perfecte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this life,<note place="margin">Ruffin. in Pſal. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> yet deſire they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlie correction, that they may goo to theire countrie ſo muche the more perfecte, by how muche
<pb facs="tcp:18721:47"/>
God correctinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth their litle ſynnes. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ruſte of ſynne is ſcoured out by correction, when the blottes of ſynne be raſed oute throughe the ſworde of perſecution, they thus perſecuted and purged, can not but come with comforte, to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ſeate of our lorde. And for that the preſente courſe of this life,<note place="margin">Grego. li. <hi>5.</hi> cap <hi>15</hi> in Iob.</note> is but the waie wher in they ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne toward theire cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie that be here paſſengers, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte they ſhould loue the waye, or thoſe thinges which they finde in the waye, in ſtede of theire countrie, they be knocked and whipped forwarde with trobles by the waye, which yet by godes good mercies, and comfortable graces, they ouercome. <hi>Al that is borne of God, ouercometh the vvorlde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5.</note> And they be ſo borne that forſake the thinges of the worlde, which be againſt God. They ouercome, that withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de concupiſcence,<note place="margin">Ber ſer. <hi>1.</hi> in octa. paſca.</note> ambition, and pridie of life, which the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:18721:47"/>
loueth. They ouercome, that forſake libertie, ſchiſme, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, which the worlde prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. And they ouercome, that ſuffer afflictions for Chriſtes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, which the worlde ſhonneth. You that be borne of God, and nowe ſuffer for Godes houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you ſuffer in the worlde, that you may not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned with the worlde.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11</note> Contente your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with this kind of ſuffering. This daylye affliction is a kinde of martyrdom, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine effuſion of bloudde, which they ſhed in a milde,<note place="margin">Ber. ſer. <hi>1</hi> in octa. paſcae.</note> but a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge martyrdome, that can not once die for Chriſte. In this prolonginge of deathe by day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie puniſhement, <hi rend="margQuotes">the diuel ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth his craftines, for ſekinge youre deathe by ſlowe and dul ſworde, he coueteth to kyl your ſoules, and not your bodies. He coueteth to take from you,</hi> the glorious name of martyrdome. But you may be martyrs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ſtroke of ſworde, yf you
<pb facs="tcp:18721:48"/>
kepe pacience in your heartes.<note place="margin">Cipr. de exhor. ad Marty. cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> For notwitſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge wee deferre the honor of martyrdome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie to them, that endure in tormentes for Chriſte euen to deathe, yet be they martyres alſo, which beare witnes of Chriſte in conuerſation of life, and confeſſion of faithe. They be called martyres, which be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente for Chriſtes ſake to ſuffer rebukes,<note place="margin">Grego. ho. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> reuiles, ſlaunders, and what perſecution of tonges ſo euer. This is the ſecret martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the minde, the other is the open martyrdome of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by deathe. That any be a martyr, God requireth not effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of bloud but faithe, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence wherof a man may dewti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie ſhedde his bloudde. And martyrdome is in worke and in wil,<note place="margin">Ber. in nata. S. Innocen. ſer. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> as it was in S. Stephan, or in wil onelie, as it was is S. Iohn Euangeliſte, or in worke onelie, as it was in the bleſſed Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. The merite of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome in S. Iohn that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:18721:48"/>
not,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. de bon. con. ca. <hi>21</hi>
               </note> and in S. Peter that ſuffered, was not vneuen. But be it that God permite the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of the worlde, to put you to open martyrdome, as ſome good and conſtant catholikes amonge you haue ben put of late yeares, then trulie aboue al, you ſhal ouercome the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and become open marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. <hi rend="margQuotes">For this is the victorie that ouercometh the worlde, fides noſtra.</hi> By this the Martyres conquered when they ſuffered.<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>2</hi> de ſerm. in Monte.</note> Thoughe they were killed in bodie, yet could they not be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to yelde in ſoule. The tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors were ouercomed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they coulde not doo what theire wil was to doo, theire wil was to kil Chriſte in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to extincte Chriſtes faithe, which thinge they coulde not doo. And therfore wee ſinge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſe of the martyres glorious triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phes. We kepe their deathe dayes, which he called theire birthe dayes, becauſe in theire
<pb facs="tcp:18721:49"/>
deathe and martyrdome, they ouercome the worlde, they be borne againe, newlie baptiſed, and beginne to liue with God in eternitie of glorie. Bleſſed and thriſe bleſſed be then, to whom God geueth his gratious gifte to ouercome the worlde by dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. It is the requital that wee can make to Chriſte, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bloud is recompenſed with bloudde,<note place="margin">Hiero. epiſt. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> and when we that were rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the pretious bloud of Chriſte, doo willinglie ſhed our bloud for him. Marye this is not in your power, but in your worthines, which is not of you, but of God. But yf God make you worthie to goo that waye, the waye is made eaſie and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne before you.<note place="margin">Aug. ſer. de temp. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> Chriſte your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de is gon that waye. Manye thouſande Martyres are gon that waye. Olde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yonge men, children, and maydes, are gon that waye. Popes, Biſhopes, prieſtes, kinges, Senators, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelors, noblemen, noble women,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:49"/>
holie widowes, deuoute virgin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, babes, and infantes, are gon that waye. Into that waye, you haue him to leade you by him ſelfe, to him ſelfe, that was made the waye for you, Ieſus Chriſt that ſaide, <hi>I am the vvaye.</hi> And when you goo that waye,<note place="margin">Cypri. de exhor. Mar cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> your eyes be cloſed in the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the earthe, the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be opened to you that be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. Antechriſte threateneth, Chriſte defendeth, deathe goeth before, life foloweth, temporal life is loſte, eternal life is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. <hi rend="margQuotes">And what comforte, what ioye, what ſecuritie, wil it be to paſſe gloriouſelie in preſſure, and ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie to ſhutte the eyes of your bodie with which you ſawe men, and by and by to open the eyes of your ſoule, to ſee your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſte.</hi> Howſoeuer it pleaſeth Godes holie wil to dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le with you, <hi>endure you vnder correction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for God offereth him ſelfe therin vnto your, as to his children.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>There is not a childe of
<pb facs="tcp:18721:50"/>
his, vvhom he correcteth not, vvhom he loueth he proueth.</hi> In this endured correction, you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue this comforte, that God ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you grace to confeſſe him, and fortitude to ſuffer for him. You haue this comforte, that there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth nothinge to you, but what you may make your profite of. Amonge manye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, this is not the leaſte, that it bringeth you to ioyne your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues near vnto God, it moueth you to do more penance, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke more prayer, to receaue more often the holie ſacramentes, by meanes and vertue of whiche, God aſſiſteth you, God ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth you, and wil make that perfecte in you, which he hath begonne. Aboue the reſte of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes which you haue in this endured affliction, the moſte ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne comforte is to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that what euer the iniquitie of time, or malice of men ſhal worke againſte you for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, you can ſuffer no more
<pb facs="tcp:18721:50"/>
then Chriſte him ſelfe ſuffered to make his churche glorious, no more then Chriſtes ſainctes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered when they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed Chriſte, and his religion, euen to deathe. Nor can you ſuffer for a better cauſe, then for which Chriſte and his ſainctes ſuffered. And how muche better is it for you ſo to ſuffer, then to liue in a falſe feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of the worlde, and to die from God, in ſchiſme and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. How lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table ſhould your loſſe be, yf nowe you ſhoulde fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the newe no faithe of the worlde, and lacke God in the worlde to come, becauſe you lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked iuſtice of faithe. You ſe how the ſtorme endureth, the ſea is trobeled, the ſhippe is te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſted, and how Chriſte ſleapeth in the ſhippe. What now muſte you doo but goo to Chriſte, as his diſciples did, awake him, as they did, ſay vnto him as they did. O lord ſaue vs. Feare you not ſo to do, for you haue Chriſte in the ſhippe with you, he is the
<pb facs="tcp:18721:51"/>
gouernor of the ſhippe, he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth you in the waye.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.</note> And your faithe (I doubte not) is nowe ſtronger then the faithe of Chriſtes diſciples was, when they were in the ſhippe with him, for they had not yet ſene the croſſe, the deathe, the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and aſcenſion of Chriſte. They coulde not but be waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe, as men that were not yet confirmed nor comforted, with the holie ghoſte. Your faithe is ſtrengthened by the frutes of thes, your faithe is confirmed, by the doctrine of the Apoſtles, by the preachinges of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, by the deathe of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, by the vniforme conſente of your forefathers, finallie by the general practiſe of the whole chriſtian worlde. You that be ſo manye wayes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed in your faithe, can not but goo vnto Chriſte with good currage, and boldelie awake him, and frelie ſaye vnto him. <hi>Domine ſalua nos.</hi> And to him muſte you become
<pb facs="tcp:18721:51"/>
humble ſupplia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, that he vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſafe to quiet the tempeſtes of the ſea, as he did at the prayers of his diſciples. As Chriſte then in rayſinge that tempeſte, did prepare the mindes of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to beare trobles, and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me their vnderſtanding to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke theire refuge vnto him, that he mighte ſhewe the mightenes of his power: Euenſo doth he ſtil diſpoſe, that greate trobles come vpon his faitheful ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, which yet he quieteth in good time, after they haue prayed vnto him. And that, we ſhoulde praye, it is his holie wil. This hath he ſaide.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt cal vpon me in the daye of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and I vvil heare thee.</hi> He ſhewed vs an example hereof, when he went in to the monute Oliuet, before his paſſion to praye. And certain it is, that prayer is of valour eyther to take awaye tribulation, or to geue ſtrenghte to beare it. <hi rend="margQuotes">Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie writers affirme, that to
<pb facs="tcp:18721:52"/>
geue ſtrengthe is a farre greater grace, then to take it awaye, and that our lorde doth more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vs, when he geueth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the to ſuſtaine perſecution, then when he taketh perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from vs.</hi> No doubte but Chriſtes diſciples which be nowe in the ſhippe windeſhaken, and ſore beaten with the cruel tempeſtes of the ſea, cal vpon him, make theire contineual praier that he voucheſafe to ariſe, to rebuke the windes, and to make calme the tempeſte. No doubte but they ſaye and daylie ſaie. Ariſe o lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, ſaue vs, and helpe vs oute of tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But for that Chriſte heareth not theire praiers by and bie, for that Chriſte releueth not their miſeries preſentlie, Chriſte ſemeth to them aſleepe, wheras in dede it is his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſpenſation, and diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, not to recomforte the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo ſone as they cal, but firſte to exerciſe, and to proue theire vertues, to proue theire faithe,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:52"/>
theire hope, theire charitie, to proue theire humilitie, pacience, and conſtancie. It is written,<note place="margin">Deut <hi>13</hi> Auguſt. tract. <hi>43.</hi> in Euan. Ioan.</note> 
               <hi>Our lorde God tempteth you to knovve vvhether you loue hym or no.</hi> that is, God maketh you to knowe whether you loue him. He knoweth you, you knowe not your ſelues, he maketh you to knowe your ſelues by iuſte trial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and proufes.<note place="margin">Idem quaeſt. <hi>60</hi> de quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtio. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note> And yet doth he not te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte you to knowe you, but permitteth you to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make you to be knowen to your ſelues and to othes, <hi rend="margQuotes">how muche you haue profited in his loue, which doubteles men can not vnderſtande, but when God trieth you.</hi> And Chriſte our lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de is ſaide to ſleape, when of his mercie he prolongeth iuſtice, when of his mercie he ſuffereth ſynners vncorrected, and iuſte liuers to be puniſhed, when he ſuffereth the euil to be exalted, and the good to be deiected, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue proſperitie and peace of the worlde, thes to finde aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:53"/>
and trobbles in the worlde. But the holie ſcripture muſte nedes be true.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 120.</note> 
               <hi>He that kepeth Iſrael doth not ſlumber, nor vvil ſleape.</hi> And therfore muſte not the afflicted leaue of to praye, thoughe God protract his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for a time to trie the conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of theire faithe and to exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe their vertues.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>13</hi> in cap. <hi>7.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at ope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nper.</note> Some thinges be not denied thoughe for a time deferred. And God deferreth for a time, to geue them in more conuenient time.<note place="margin">Grego. in Iob li <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> God deferreth that the yl affection of our hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes might be better purged, and that the thinges which wee lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge for,<note place="margin">Auguſt. Ver. <hi>1.</hi> de verb. do.</note> might be better welcome when they be obtained. Thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that be obtayned eaſelie, be leſſe regarded. <hi rend="margQuotes">God kepeth for vs in ſtore what he wyl not geue by and bye,</hi> that we may learne to longe for greate thinges, with longe and greate deſire. I crye (ſaith Iob) and thou heareſt me not. I ſtande and thou lokeſt not on mee. In tyme of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:18721:53"/>
the holie churche ſtandeth in faithe, and crieth in deſire.<note place="margin">Grego in Iob lib. <hi>20.</hi> c <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> But God almightie (ſuch is his hidden iudgement and ſecret cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel) vſeth to defer the praiers of them that be perſecuted, to the entente their merites might encreaſe, and they be heard ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to their merite, then to their deſire. And it helpeth to encreaſe the vnderſtandinge of godlie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their deſires be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed, but after a tyme. <hi rend="margQuotes">For deſire kindeleth of delaie, and</hi> vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge encreaſeth of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. We muſt aſke, we muſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, we muſte knocke. Our lorde hath ſaide. <hi>Aſke you, and you ſhal receaue. Seeke and you ſhal finde. Knocke and the doore ſhal be opened.</hi> Wee muſt perſeauer eager and feruente in prayer, not doubtinge but in tyme we ſhal receaue what we aſke, in tyme we ſhal finde what wee ſeeke, and after wee haue knocked, the doore wil be opened. That ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ladie of conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and quene
<pb facs="tcp:18721:54"/>
of comforte, with al the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie courte to whom you ſo often poure forthe your mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge plaintes, wyl not wante to make interceſſion for you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throwne of his maieſtie. Theire praiers wyl not faile, but gaine you comforte in your diſtreſſes. And aſſure your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that God wyl heare you, and them for you, for he is al wayes nighe to them that be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. Chriſte may ſeeme longe a ſleepe to you that be afflicted, to you it may ſeeme timelie that Chriſte take pitie of his churche ſo pitiouſlie afflicted with here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and tyrannie. But it is not our parte to appointe him time, he knoweth beſte what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for vs. To him wee muſte humble our ſoules, and praye for ſuche times, as may be moſte for his honor. It was ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to them of Bethulia,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudith</hi> 4</note> 
               <hi>Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande you that God vvil heare your prayers, yf ſtil you perſeuere in faſtinge and prayer.</hi> God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie
<pb facs="tcp:18721:54"/>
hath appointed tyme, and knoweth when and how to deliuer the Godlie out of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Tob.</hi> 3.</note> After a ſtorme he maketh fayre wether. After weepinge and heuines, he geueth mirthe and ioye. The ſhippe hath ben ſhaken with no leſſe ſtormes at other times, then at this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Chriſte quieted thoſe, and Chriſte wil quiet thes. Doubte you not but he wil bringe his trobeled freindes throughe the middes of thes tempeſtes, and repoſe them in quiet hauen. I conclude with thes conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Chriſtians are nowe put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as it were in apotte ouer the fire to be tried, as goulde is tried from other metalles. The fire flameth, the pot ſeetheth, the waters be thicke, the ſcombe is caſte awaye.</p>
            <p>Catholikes are in the forge <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vnder the workemans hande to be refined. They are in the forge
<pb facs="tcp:18721:55"/>
not as coles that burne and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to aſhes, but as golde that is tried. The forge is the worlde, you are the golde, tribulation is the fire, God is the worke man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Chriſtian catholike life conſiſteth in ſufferinge, wee muſt not therfore doo our owne wil, but the wil of God. And amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge men wee muſt eyther ſuffer the rulers wil or theire power, their wil to order vs, or theire power to puniſhe vs. And then the conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is, eyther to haue victorie in this worlde, or to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render this life, to inherite the life euerlaſtinge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The ſureſte waye to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the peaceable porte of our countrie, (towarde which wee ſaile toſſed in many tempeſtes) is, to remaine in the ſhippe, and in the ſame to trace the true wayes of them that haue gon before, to treade in their ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, and to become heires of their vertues.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18721:55"/>Hard thinges may be molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſtraite thinges may be louſed, and heauie thinges ſhal litle greue them, that can beare them hanſomlie.</p>
            <p>Thoughe God ſuffer for a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> time the wicked to rage, and the hypocrite to raigne, yet the ſame hande that woundeth heyleth, the ſame hande that preſſeth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth. Godes pitiful grace wyl quenche the firebrandes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage the rage, and releue the innocentes.</p>
            <p>The wiſedome of the worlde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> maketh worldlie heades deffecte from God. Good mens hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes be create of God, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteles in the worlde, but when they reſte in God.</p>
            <p>As there is but one God, one <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> faithe, and one baptiſme, ſo is there but one Chriſte, one chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and one religion. No faithe can profite but that one, which is the catholike Romaine fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, confeſſed in the catholike
<pb facs="tcp:18721:56"/>
Romaine churche, that is but one, vnder one heade. The Lutheran, the Caluinian, and Puritan faithe, is a newe no fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, a newe no religion, founded vpon mannes fancie, <hi rend="margQuotes">without Godes worde or authoritie. It hath no churche, no biſhoppe, no prieſte, no aulter, no ſacrifice, and conſequentlie no God.</hi> And they of this newe no faithe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge no grounde in Chriſte, nor of his churche, diſſente in their owne groundes, without vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from veritie. You haue the groundes of Chriſte. You haue the authoritie of Chriſtes chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. You haue the teſtimonies of Chriſtes ſainctes. You haue the confirmations, of general coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles. With you is the vniforme conſente of the people of God. With you is the publike practiſe of the Chriſtian worlde. You ſhould not be diſcomforted to ſuffer for ſuch a cauſe, as hath ſo manye greate, ſo manye good, and ſo ſufficience groundes, for
<pb facs="tcp:18721:56"/>
ſuche a cauſe (I ſaye) as with which concurre ſo manye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes. As that you ſuſtaine the greateſte cauſe under the cope of heauen, the common cauſe of Chriſtes catholike churche, the cauſe of religion, which is the ſupreme ſeruice and ſoueraigne honor, that you can offer vnto God. That God maketh you worthie, geueth you grace to confeſſe, and fortitude to ſuffer. That you enioye in the vnitie of Chriſtes churche, the bountie of his bleſſinges. That you be ſafe in this churche, throughe the mightie power of your guides and rulers. That you be perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of al praier, of al ſacrifice, of al good workes, and ſhal be pertakers of Chriſtes deathe and merites. That in ſufferinge you be daylie crowned, that you haue victorie, and ſhal haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. That in ſufferinge, your vertues be exerciſed, and your merites encreaſed. That you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer directelie for iuſtice, that you
<pb facs="tcp:18721:57"/>
ſuffer but for a time. That by ſuffering God maketh you lowe, to bringe you to the higheſt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth you ritche in faithe, and turneth your temporal puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to your ſpiritual benefite. That you ouercome the worlde, that you ſhal not be condemned with the worlde. That you be open confeſſors. That you haue ſecrete martyrdome, that you haue al poſſible comfortes with which faithe is ſtrengthened to make you ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Martyres. Yf any of you take comforte in any of thes comfortes, geue the praiſe to God, and cal vpon him in al your preſſures and ſufferinges. God wil be your helpe and God muſte be your hope. Yf there be remedie, it wil once fal, yf there be none, thanke God of al. Bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue wel, and liue wel. Do wel and die wel, that you may die to liue with God. God the father of al mercies, and the God of al com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, comforte you in al your tribulation with the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte,
<pb facs="tcp:18721:57"/>
wherwith our ſelues are comforted of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Fare you wel. At Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaine, <date>the laſt of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember. 1579.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer.</head>
            <p>Almightie God father of al mercies, and God of al comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, haue mercie on vs the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted members, of thy catholike churche. Forgeue vs our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, geue vs tyme to do penance, grace to reſiſte ſynne, and peace to ſerue thee in holynes. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte vs that be thy priſoners, reliue vs that be ſtraingers in diſperſion, ſuccour al that be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, for confeſſinge thy holie name. Make vs worthie to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, geue vs ſtrengthe to beare, and conſtancie to confeſſe. Let no feare, nor force remoue vs, from thy vnitie. Let no crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:18721:58"/>
of the diuel deceaue vs, nor deuiſe of man, ouercome vs. Diſcerne (O lorde) thy cauſe, humble thy enemies, recomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te thy freindes, that they maye geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes vnto thee, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy name, in thy holie chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Graunte this (O lorde) for Chriſtes ſake our lorde, that ſuffered bitter deathe, to make his churche glorious.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="Scriptural_citations">
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:58"/>
            <q>
               <p>He that taketh not hys croſſe and foloweth mee, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of mee.</p>
               <bibl>Math. 10.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Jesus carrying the cross</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Al that vvil liue godlie in Christ, ſhal ſuffer perſecutions.</p>
               <bibl>2. Tim. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Yf the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſuffer not for Chriſt, vvaigh whether you haue yet begone to liue godlie in Christ.</p>
               <bibl>August. in Pſal. 57.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <pb facs="tcp:18721:59"/>Hanc epiſtolam conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latoriam, ex fide duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum presbyterorum Anglorum, quorum integritas &amp; eruditio nobis cognita eſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cudi poſſe cenſeo.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Ioh. Molanus, cenſor.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18721:59"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the Crucifixion</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>God forbid that I ſhould glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in any thinge, but in the croſſe of our lorde Ieſu Christe.</p>
               <bibl>Gal. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18721:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
